<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>Do. Reflect. Learn. Repeat!</title>
    <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</link>
    <description>Excercises in public learning</description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 08:41:17 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>Dahon Bullhead with Aerobars</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/03/22/dahon-bullhead-with-aerobars/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2012 17:37:49 CET</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[aerobars]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[cycling]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[bicycle]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[gear]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[dahon]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[bullhead]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/03/22/dahon-bullhead-with-aerobars/</guid>
      <description>Dahon Bullhead with Aerobars</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
<p>After converting my Neuzer Courier DT fitness bike to use drop bars, I swore never again to do that, but just buy a road bike instead.</p>
<p>However, since bike transportation is hard, I chose my commuter folding bike for the trip from Germany to Budapest.</p>
<p>However, the roughly 150km/day does require multiple hand positions, and I'm a roadie at heart, so no butterflies for me.</p>
<p>That left the aerobar :) While initially I was concerned since a) I've never had one before b) my bike has 20" wheels; the local bike store was kind enough to suggest that I buy one, take it for a short, few hours test, and if unhappy with it, they refund it.</p>
<p>And I've learned that aerobars are the best thing since sliced bread.</p>
<p>I got used to it fast, and while it is not usable in as many situations as drop bars are (don't use it in traffic/crowd, even if you've got fixie-trained traffic senses, since you got no brakes!), it does give a racing feeling to an otherwise normal bike :)</p>
<p>Adjusting the thing took forever though, so I actually went back to the store and upgraded to a single piece one, since I do fold the bike daily (the picture is with the old one).</p>
<p>And yes, I know it looks odd. But I am after functionality, not beauty!</p>
<p><a href="/2012/03/wp_000234.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-8" height="225" src="/2012/03/wp_000234.jpg?w=300" title="wp 000234" width="300"/></a></p>

          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/03/22/dahon-bullhead-with-aerobars/">Dahon Bullhead with Aerobars</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
