<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>Do. Reflect. Learn. Repeat!</title>
    <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</link>
    <description>Excercises in public learning</description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 08:41:17 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>The Power of (Open Source) Blueprints</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2015/12/05/the-power-of-open-source-blueprints/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2015 13:41:00 CET</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[organizing]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[community]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[citcon]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[change]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[teaching]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[coderetreat]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">TmQscoJEA-SD6hw3sIe4T-DcJt4=</guid>
      <description>The Power of (Open Source) Blueprints</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          <h2 id="what-are-blueprints">What are blueprints</h2>
<p>As per Wikipedia, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blueprint">blueprint</a> is something that <em>allowed
rapid and accurate reproduction of documents</em>. I have heard it used (and
used myself) for processes too.</p>
<p>They are powerful because they allow me or anyone else to recreate
someone else's tried and tested idea, which in turn allows the idea
to spread (scale) to unimaginable numbers and reach places (and provide
benefits to) the original inventor could have never dreamed of.</p>
<p>It allows a complete novice to the field to organize a successful event.
Think of it like a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franchising">franchise</a>. You yourself do put in the
work, and your success benefits the franchise as well as yourself.
However, you don't have to start from scratch; you have a process you
follow, that has been proven to work. When advertising your event, there
is the social proof that the brand exists that makes it easier to sell
it.</p>
<h2 id="examples">Examples</h2>
<p>Some such blueprints I've come across and worked with are</p>
<ul>
<li>the <a href="http://citconf.com/">CITCON</a> meta wiki about <a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=ConferencePlanning">organizing the open space
  conference</a> - and <a href="http://citconf.com/archive/budapest2012//">CITCON Budapest</a> was
  quite a success, which I couldn't have pulled off without having
  the process to follow</li>
<li><a href="http://coderetreat.org/">Coderetreats</a> - I've participated and facilitated in
  public &amp; firm-internal events. The educational sessions and the superb
  detailed documentation the coderetreat community provides make it
  almost too easy to run such an event - no surprise that in 2015 there
  were <a href="http://coderetreat.org/events/event/listByType?type=gdcr15">at least 158 events</a> on a single day!</li>
<li><a href="https://djangogirls.org/">Django Girls</a> - it started in June 2014 in Berlin, and
  by now it already took place on all continents - simply because they 
  have a wonderfully detailed tutorial on how to organize such an event!</li>
<li>the <a href="http://alistair.cockburn.us/Elephant+carpaccio">Elephant Carpaccio</a> also has a super detailed
  <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TCuuu-8Mm14oxsOnlk8DqfZAA1cvtYu9WGv67Yj_sSk/pub">facilitation guide</a></li>
</ul>
<p>... but I'm sure there are many more out there.</p>
<h2 id="benefits">Benefits</h2>
<p>If you are trying to bring change in your company/team, but you haven't
done it before, you don't have to necessarily invent workshops yourself
(of course, if you want, you can), but can simply take off established
ones "from the shelf".</p>
<p><em>Caution</em>: while you could theoretically run an event just from the
tutorials, it might be beneficial to have attended such a workshop
before running it. I've cooked my first <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paella"><em>paella</em></a> from a 
cookbook, without ever having eaten one before. While everyone agreed
I've cooked something delicious, later we had to acknowledge it had 
little to do with a real paella :)</p>
<h2 id="if-you-are-already-organizing-something">If you are already organizing something</h2>
<p>If you can afford it, I highly suggest you publicly document it (and
license it openly), so others have a chance to do the same. E.g.: many
user groups struggle finding speakers or sponsors - it would be great to
have a handbook on your sponsor/speaker attraction tactics. It won't
take away from the success of your event or the benefits to your
reputation, you simply just enable more people elsewhere to do the same!</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2015/12/05/the-power-of-open-source-blueprints/">The Power of (Open Source) Blueprints</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
