<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>Do. Reflect. Learn. Repeat!</title>
    <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</link>
    <description>Excercises in public learning</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 18:11:20 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>CITCON Cluj 2016</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2016/04/18/citcon-cluj-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 12:32:00 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[citcon]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[conferences]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Ak8DsCUnbn3-fj05vbRCp36P4OI=</guid>
      <description>CITCON Cluj 2016</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          <style type="text/css">
.post img {
   width: 100%;
   height: auto;
}
</style>

<div class="toc">
<ul>
<li><a href="#monorepos">Monorepos</a></li>
<li><a href="#is-there-a-limit-to-self-organization">Is there a limit to self organization?</a></li>
<li><a href="#randomized-testingrandom-data-generation">Randomized testing/random data generation</a></li>
<li><a href="#continuous-deliverydeploymnet-side-effects">Continuous Delivery/Deploymnet side effects</a></li>
<li><a href="#how-do-you-test-your-organization">How do you test your organization?</a></li>
<li><a href="#elephant-carpaccio">Elephant Carpaccio</a></li>
<li><a href="#summary">Summary</a></li>
<li><a href="#books-of-citcon-cluj">Books of CITCON Cluj</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
<p>Cluj was the seventh CITCON I attended, and it's the second CITCON organized by people who first attended the conference series in Budapest (which I organized :)). But it's not about reunion of old friends, it's a super open and welcoming event, where I still keep learning, so without further ado, here are my learnings from the sessions I've attended.</p>
<h2 id="monorepos">Monorepos</h2>
<p>(It was a lunch session, which I didn't attend, but we've talked about it Friday evening)</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/ivanrmoore">Ivan Moore</a> suggested (and has done so in his past project(s)) not to break up your team's repo into different repos, but just have a single one and keep modules separated. Essentially he suggests a single repo per team.</p>
<p>The benefit of this is that you save a lot of time by not having to deal with a bunch of things, especially in the build, packaging and dependency versioning/management area - the compatible versions are always kept together.</p>
<p>It's recommended that you CD the artifacts, but it's actually not a requirement.</p>
<p>We disagreed whether the physical separation  of repos is a better tool to teach people proper modularization, Ivan argued that it should be addressed on a team dynamic/process level (reviews, pairing, etc.), and not make delivery (and refactoring) harder. Note on refactoring: in Java, the equivalent of <code>pip install -e &lt;folder|git url&gt;</code> is much less practical than in Python.</p>
<h2 id="is-there-a-limit-to-self-organization">Is there a limit to self organization?</h2>
<p>It turns out that the team I work with is quite self organizing, but only within the unit of the team. <a href="https://twitter.com/jtf">@Jtf</a> suggested to rephrase the question as <em>Is there a limit to self organization or only to how big the self is?</em>.</p>
<p>I also learned that one should be careful with terminology - the question of who owns the solution and who owns the goal is totally orthogonal to how any given team is organizes work.</p>
<p>At <a href="https://twitter.com/jtf">@Jtf</a>'s company they run something similar to how <a href="http://www.valvesoftware.com/jobs/index.html">Valve</a> operates - there is an internal project fair, where PO(s) propose projects, and then developers sign up for them - and it's perfectly OK if a project gets no signups.</p>
<p>To address the divide between who owns the goal and who the solution, properly cross functional teams can be the answer, i.e.: the PO should be part of the team and should really own goals and priorization of the goals.</p>
<p>There was a rather interesting quote from Alistair Cockburn that <a href="http://alistair.cockburn.us/Self-organization+means+mutiny">"Self organization is mutiny"</a>, because self organizing will inevitebly be pushing the boundaries.</p>
<p>The technique called <a href="http://blog.jeffreyfredrick.com/2016/04/08/coherence-busting-explained/">Coherence Busting</a> was suggested, which in high level translates to empathy/understanding where people's actions are coming from, i.e.: What has to be true for this behavior to make sense. But if you can, just ask directly :)</p>
<h2 id="randomized-testingrandom-data-generation">Randomized testing/random data generation</h2>
<p>On the train ride to Cluj, I was <a href="https://github.com/zsoldosp/spike-pytest-fixtures">playing around with py.test's test fixtures</a> and how one can combine that, e.g.: in a shopping cart, how can one specify in a test that "I need an order for an electroncics items that is sold to an end user who paid by credit card and who used a fixed amount coupon". I've found that generating all combinations is rather easy, but to filter out the scenarios I need for a given test is hard if I don't want to write a lot of specific fixtures (e.g.: <code>electronics_item_for_end_user_with_creditcard_with_fixed_discount</code>), which could get out of hand fast.</p>
<p>One possibility could be to do some (model driven) code generation to generate all these specific fixtures, but I had the impression it might become unmaintainable/hard to understand quickly.</p>
<p>During the session, I used the analogy that "as if I was writing a SQL query to select the test scenarios I need", which - with the input from the other participants led to the realization that I could separate the generation of scenarios from the selection of scenarios, i.e.: I could generate all possible combinations, serialize the results somewhere before running the tests, and then inside the tests I could just query the generated ones and load them. Certainly something to experiment with further!</p>
<h2 id="continuous-deliverydeploymnet-side-effects">Continuous Delivery/Deploymnet side effects</h2>
<p>This session was run by <a href="http://www.pauljulius.com/">PJ</a>, CTO of an online advertising firm, who described their one year journey to CD, and the kind of interesting side effects he has observed.</p>
<p>He has mapped out the full process from idea to profit, and looked where they could speed it up. As a CTO, he started in the domain under his control, i.e.: from commit to released to production, though as it turned out, that's quite a small slice of the full process. Later when he showed the chart to fellow executives, they were surprised by the complexity of the project. Most likely it was the result of organic growth that comes from the human/firm behavior that when one encounters a problem/road block, often the solution to fix it is to add more process to it. Quickly there was buyin to automate a solution to the root causes for which the processes were introduced.</p>
<p><img alt="Paul Julius describing an ideas path from idea to profit" src="/img/citcon-cluj/pj-cd-side-effects.jpg" /></p>
<p>PJ told the engineers to spend the bulk of their coding time refactoring. Which people initially didn't. So he then <em>required that 50% of the time was to be spent on refactoring, as well as 50% of the time should be pair programming</em>. The business did protest initially (this was before the full value map), but the results quickly proved it was worth it. Before this change, it took 12.5 days to from a time the story made it to the implementation backlog to production down to 3.5 days (average), which led to happy stakeholders.</p>
<p>They achieved this by:</p>
<ul>
<li>integrating devs, testers, operations, etc. into a mixed teams, now everyone's title is "Software Creator"</li>
<li>slicing stories smaller</li>
<li>ship the done story when it's done, and not the end of the two weeks iteration</li>
<li>to fill out the refactoring time, they've actually reduced the pure build time from 90 minutes to 3 minutes, and the commit to build ready feedback cycle from 2.5 hours (due to pending builds) to just under a cup of coffeee</li>
</ul>
<p>PJ's observation is that if you give people metrics to strive for, they will game the system to achieve it, so if you give the right targets, great things will happen (note: it's not always easy to get the right targets :))</p>
<p>The refactoring eliminated the fear people had before to change the codebase.</p>
<p>Once they got to the time where it took 3 minutes to deploy, and 1 minute to roll back, the team actually decided to get rid of the slow end to end tests, as they could get faster feedback from production than the time it took to run those tests. However, as an online ad agency, they do have 1000s of events per second (or minutes), so they have enough data. We couldn't pin down an exact formula when exactly one can switch to production monitoring to replace their end to end tests, but the ratio of the time the team needs to go from change idea to deploy in production (<code>i2p</code>, idea to production) and the time the team needs to get feedback whether the change was good once it was deployed (<code>p2f</code>, production to feedback) is a useful one to consider where to invest your time. E.g.: if <code>i2p</code> = 30 mins and <code>p2f</code> is 3 minutes, optimizing <code>i2p</code> could make sense. But if <code>i2p</code> is an hour, and <code>p2f</code> is a day, maybe it doesn't. If anyone knows of some mathematics that could help here, please let me know!</p>
<p>As they dropped their end to end tests tests, unit tests did skyrocket in number too.</p>
<p>Also, just to emphasize, while in retrospect and in this presentation it could sound like smooth sailing, it wasn't, there were many mistakes. But that quickly teaches the team to focus on resiliency and recovery, i.e.: they changed there processes around to reduce the cost of an error (fine-grained feature flags (on off, enable for only some groups, etc.), rolling out to a few servers and then to the whole cluster, etc.). </p>
<p>Apparently New Relic supports a/b testing with monitoring, so one could compare the new release against the old one, so that's something to look into.</p>
<h2 id="how-do-you-test-your-organization">How do you test your organization?</h2>
<p><img alt="Andy Parker's notes from the session" src="/img/citcon-cluj/ap-testing-your-org.jpg" /></p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/aparker42">Andy Parker</a> is an engineering manager in a self organizing organization, so the question arose: what exactly should a manager do there? His answer is to gather data that could be an additional input into the kaizen (continuous improvement).</p>
<p>When one joins the organization, it helps to map out the company - look at the org chart, as well as how actually work gets done. Who are the key communicators? Who are people actually working with (usually across the hierarchy, even whent he only common manager they have is the CEO). This is easy to do when one is starting out, but should be remembered an actualized even when one is already part of the "daily mill". See also: static vs. dynamic org. situation</p>
<p>Before one starts out collecting organization, one should always start with a hypothesis (as per the scientific method). This can be the null hypothesis, i.e.: there is nothing interesting here, so observing it I'll find that everything is OK and I will just confirm that.</p>
<p>Some tools to do this is</p>
<ul>
<li>take notes - raw data when possible, even though you can't be an impartial observer of course</li>
<li>beware that observation changes things, but that in itself can be valuable information. E.g.: oh, people are pairing there, let's see what they are working on! Hmm, now that I observe them, they stopped pairing and went back to working alone. Why is that?</li>
<li>(with permission), record conversations and re-listen to them</li>
<li>
<p>in a meeting, draw a communication matrix -</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>who talks to whom</p>
</li>
<li>are they making statements or questions?</li>
<li>
<p>how long do they talk?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>interview team members - what is your responsibility in the team? what is others' responsibility? You can find that not everyone has the same understaning</p>
</li>
<li>one, especially developers/engineers, should be careful to start with qualitative analysis, and not quantitative</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="elephant-carpaccio">Elephant Carpaccio</h2>
<p>It's a workshop that was <a href="http://alistair.cockburn.us/Elephant+carpaccio">originally run by Alistair Cockburn</a>, but <a href="http://douglassquirrel.com/">Douglas Squirrel</a> has adopted it to fit the one hour session limit.</p>
<p>As we've walked into the room, everyone was required to add a single feature to the drawing of an elephant (which started out as with a circle (head) and 4 lines (body, two legs, and the trump)). Surely we didn't create the masterpiece, but it started to resemble the elephant more and more, and as Squirrel observed, it was looking like an elephant throughout the whole process, it was just getting better/more detailed with each iteration.</p>
<p><img alt="Squirrel showing the original and final elphants" src="/img/citcon-cluj/squirrel-elephants.jpg" /></p>
<p>His client is working with a simple kanban board that has the following columns: idea, dev working on it, testing, and live. Their goal is (which they meet more often than not) to go from idea to live in a single developer day for a story.</p>
<p>E.g.: their app shows graphs, and they've introduced the color picker to allow users to choose the color of the lines of their graph via the following cards:</p>
<ul>
<li>behind a feature toggle, release a UI button for the color picker (to learn whether or not people will actually click on it)</li>
<li>when clicked, pop up a static image (to learn whether people just close the dialog, or actually click on a color)</li>
<li>a functional color picker widget, which allows choosing a color, but the selected value is not used anywhere (to do UX testing with real users over the phone)</li>
<li>actually persist the selected color and display that on the graph (done)</li>
</ul>
<p>In each step, they've implemented a slice which either provided value or provided fast feedback. One benefit of fast feedback is that you can discover early enough if you are working on a feature noone needs, and can concentrate your efforts elsewhere. As opposed to layered development, where first the data storage is implemented, then the backend is implemented, and finally something is shown to the users. It's important to slice the elephant not parallel to the ground, but vertically along the line from its trump to it tail, so that it keeps looking like an elephant.</p>
<p>Slices work even if you only release them internally or to selected users only.</p>
<p>It's important how you slice - e.g.: one could say we start with a single (or two) color(s) color picker, but that would require us to implement a rather thick slice.</p>
<p>There is a nice <a href="http://agileforall.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/Story-Splitting-Flowchart.pdf">flowchart to decide on how to slice stories</a>.</p>
<p>In Squirrel's experience people don't tend to slice too thin, but rather they often slice the wrong way</p>
<p>There can be tension and tradeoff in slicing whether we take the smallest next slice to implement or we take the thing that gets us to market/money fastest. That's why the slicing session happens together with the PO and the devs.</p>
<p>The benefit of this approach is that estimation is eliminated, and delivery becomes more predicatable (each card is one dev day).</p>
<p>Usually they only plan ahead like a week or so, so they can respond to feedback without too much rework.</p>
<p>Context: his client is a startup still getting to the proper product - market fit.</p>
<p>After this overview, we did a slicing/planning session for a price calculator (each drink has a price, and there is vat, which varies from country to country).</p>
<p>The following cards were derived:</p>
<ul>
<li>calculate price on command line, in ireland only, for 1 pint of beer with a fixed price and fixed percent tax</li>
<li>for <code>N</code> beers</li>
<li>at a variable price (coming from the user)</li>
<li>move from the command line to a (web) API (assume CD infrastructure is present already)</li>
<li>and whisky and  wine, but calculation can only be done for a single type at a time</li>
<li>multiple types per calculation</li>
<li>expand to have the UK prices/taxes too</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>CITCON Cluj was a blast, I've learned way more than what I squeezed into this blog post, so many thanks to Adina and the local organizers for finding a great venue and making the event happen! </p>
<p>Hope to see you at a CITCON next year!</p>
<h2 id="books-of-citcon-cluj">Books of CITCON Cluj</h2>
<p>These are books that were recommended either during the sessions or conversations around the conf, in no particular order</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.strategy-business.com/article/00344?gko=10921">The Future Of Management Is Teal</a></li>
<li>Why we can't learn anything from Google / Toyota (???)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Jonathan-Lethem-Author-Occasional-Music/dp/B0036YCMOE/">Gun, with Occassional Music</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Research-Methods-Anthropology-Qualitative-Quantitative/dp/0759108692/">Research methods in anthropolgy - qualitative and quantitative approaches</a></li>
</ul>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2016/04/18/citcon-cluj-2016/">CITCON Cluj 2016</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CITCON Turin Session Notes</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2013/10/08/citcon-turin-session-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 13:30:00 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[citcon]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[conferences]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">AWskB6wuNpU0UUAq1fII-TJYmS0=</guid>
      <description>CITCON Turin Session Notes</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          <p>Finally got around to adding my notes for the <a href="/2013/09/30/citcon-turin-2013/">CITCON Turin 
2013</a> sessions to the 
<a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=CITCONEurope2013Sessions">wiki</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Are_we_doing_improvement_wrong%3F">Are we doing improvement wrong?</a></li>
<li><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Continuous_Interruptions">Continuous Interruptions</a></li>
<li><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=What_does_the_ideal_look_like%3F">What does the ideal look like?</a></li>
<li><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Low_level_test_code_/_library_bleeding_edge">Low level test code / library bleeding edge / beyond assertEquals</a></li>
<li><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Questions_on_the_right_level_and_amount_of_testing">What is code coverage good for? / Are we testing too much? / Does consolidated tree based test execution make sense?</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="notes-on-my-note-taking">Notes on my note taking</h2>
<p>... or what took me so long to add the notes? Why didn't I take notes 
directly in the conference wiki?</p>
<p>After my second attended conference I became an analog/offline attendee.
Note taking is much easier by hand - you can draw, arrow things into the
right place, and I find deciphering abbreviations and shorthand much 
easier in handwriting than in on-screen text.</p>
<p>I don't like having a screen separating me from other attendees (and 
cannot type on tablet keyboards effectively).</p>
<p>Having to type up my written notes later forces me to revisit ideas in
more detail than if I'm just re-reading old notes where I might skip 
parts thinking "sure, I know what that was". It's a mind trick to force 
me paying closer attention.</p>
<p>On top of that, I become much more careful about what I put down into 
the notes - sure, it's still rather raw and nowhere near blog post or
article quality, still much closer to raw notes/brain dumps. But it's
much improved compared to the raw notes I had in my notebook. Having the
handwritten pages only makes sure I know it is <em>not</em> DONE, which I might
fall into thinking had I written directly into the wiki.</p>
<p>Of course, that's just me, your mileage may vary!</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2013/10/08/citcon-turin-session-notes/">CITCON Turin Session Notes</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CITCON Turin 2013</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2013/09/30/citcon-turin-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2013 09:13:00 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[citcon]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[conferences]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">HBw_qzJLfvKDJyuEPItoFPtvMx8=</guid>
      <description>CITCON Turin 2013</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          <blockquote>
<p>Prior <a href="http://citconf.com/">CITCON</a> experience posts:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2010/11/my-citcon-london-2010-experience.html">London 2010</a></li>
<li><a href="/2011/11/citcon-london-2011.html">London 2011</a></li>
<li><a href="http://citconf.com/budapest2012">Budapest 2012</a> - didn't get around
  to blog about it - since I was the local organizer, by the end of 
  the conf I depleted my energy reserves :)</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>Briefly about the conference - the open space format is still the best
thing since sliced bread as far conferences go, and CITCON still brings
together wonderfully smart people. Year after year I leave it being 
thankful for pointing me to questions (and answers) waaay outside the 
proverbial box....</p>
<h2 id="sessions-attended">Sessions attended</h2>
<p>This post does not contain <a href="/2013/10/08/citcon-turin-session-notes/">session notes</a> (I'm adding them to the 
<a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/">wiki</a>) but rather just tries to convey the atmosphere/feel
of the sessions.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Are_we_doing_improvement_wrong%3F">Are we doing improvement wrong</a></strong>? Proposed by <a href="https://twitter.com/Jeffrey">Jeffrey</a>, 
  inspired by the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Toyota-Kata-Managing-Improvement-Adaptiveness/dp/0071635238/">Toyota Kata</a> book, it described the two 
  Katas, and illustrated why measuring improvement by the output 
  (results) only can lead to missed improvement opportunities (e.g.: the
  book describes that before an improvement effort, line managers were 
  called in for troubleshooting 1000 times a shift, which then decreases
  two 700 a shift. The leadership's response was that this means either</p>
<ul>
<li>people are hiding or working around failures, which is bad</li>
<li>people stopped improving, which is bad too</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>so they adjusted the workload to enable taking full advantage of
  the bandwidth of 1000 improvements/introspections the factory was
  capable of.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Continuous_Interruptions">Continuous interruptions</a></strong> Proposed by <a href="https://twitter.com/KishenPanday">Kishen</a>, we dug deep
  into how interruptions can be a wonderful tool for knowledge sharing,
  mentoring and how they hide (or to be more precise, expose) risk 
  factors. I wish I had mentioned the urban legend about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/QWERTY#cite_ref-5">the QWERTY 
  keyboard layout's design origin</a>, but the point about 
  interruptions slowing you down enough to force taking a step back 
  didn't need analogies. And it seems we all have colleagues whose cell
  phones only ring when their owners, unlike the phones, are not 
  present...</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=What_does_the_ideal_look_like%3F">What does the ideal software development process look like?</a></strong> 
  proposed by <a href="https://twitter.com/aparker42">Andrew Parker</a>, closely linked to the first
  session of the day about improvement (towards the ideal one to one
  flow) is probably the one session that I left with more questions
  than answers - not just about the topic, or its conclusions (shorten
  the cycle time (effort) required for going from idea to getting
  feedback), but even about the open spaces framework (what if the 
  scribe wants to apply the law of two feet?).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Low_level_test_code_/_library_bleeding_edge">Low level unit testing/assertion code patterns</a></strong> proposed by me,
  driven by my desire to learn what new ideas are present in this
  space. While I haven't learned of any new patterns, I left with a 
  much better understanding of how language embedded and enforced pre-
  and post-conditions (or code contracts in the C# world) can actually
  been tested, contrary to my initial assumption</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Questions_on_the_right_level_and_amount_of_testing">Are we testing too much? / What's the point of code coverage? /
  Would a Test Tree Builder and Executor make sense?</a></strong> - this was a 
  merge of three topics, proposed by <a href="https://twitter.com/KishenPanday">Kishen</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/ajmolenaar">Arjan</a>,
  and myself. It was the smallest session in attendance (it was the
  three of us and <a href="https://twitter.com/sietstweets">Cirilo</a>, with <a href="https://twitter.com/Jeffrey">Jeffrey</a> also popping by
  towards the end), but true to the spirit of open spaces, we were
  totally engaged. Plus <a href="https://twitter.com/Jeffrey">Jeffrey</a> demonstrated the need for more
  effectively transmitting information (when we brought him up to speed
  of what is being discussed, he just said "CITCON Australia 2009") or
  prior art - there is a kind of generational gap that exists between 
  programmer generations that could benefit from a few more bridges
  (though leaving enough of a divide so that people will still work on
  and solve problems that were previously declared "unsolvable"!).</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Had I not proposed any sessions, I would have loved to attend <em><a href="https://twitter.com/sf105">Steve 
Freeman</a>'s TDD Clinic</em> - it's always a pleasure to see great 
people perform, not to mention the learning opportunity. I also would
have liked to listen to <em><a href="https://twitter.com/ivanrmoore">Ivan Moore</a> describing the build setup
they have for their multi componented system</em> at work - I faced that 
problem years ago, topped with the plugin compatibility across multiple
versions problem, so would have loved to see what they did. And next 
time I'm in Budapest, I'll probably try to visit <a href="http://prezi.com">Prezi</a> again 
in case Jayson is around so I could take another look at their <code>fkt</code> 
system (and to listen to the <em><code>please</code>, <code>simply</code>, and <code>fkt</code> machine 
provisioning evolution story</em> again).  Luckily, <a href="https://twitter.com/zeljkofilipin">Zejko</a>'s 
session's about how <a href="https://wikipedia.org/">Wikipedia</a> tests there system is easy to
find online, since - like everything else <a href="https://wikipedia.org/">Wikipedia</a> does -,
it is open. But as I always say, it's so much better to leave a conf 
with too many good sessions than one with too little...</p>
<p>Another great aspect of CITCON is the dinner afterwards - even though
it splits into multiple small groups, it's real nice to talk with people
directly, both about non-tech (like explaining why it would
make a ton of sense for the Budapest Opera House to organize a summer
Opera festival) and tech (thanks to all who listened to my pet project 
ideas, and gave really useful feedback!)</p>
<p>The reunion-like feeling <a href="https://twitter.com/PaulJulius">PJ</a> mentioned during his opening remarks
was true for me too, but sadly I haven't prepared enough - I should have
organized more explicit catch-up sessions outside the conference, for I
couldn't chat with everyone I wanted to in enough depth - hard to do
when we are running additional sessions even during the lunch break!
Plus of course one doesn't want to give the conference itself an 
exclusive atmosphere - I still vividly remember my nervousness at my 
first CITCON, trying to overcome the inherent shyness to talk to people,
attempting to join their conversations...</p>
<p>In closing, I would like to thank <a href="https://twitter.com/capotribu">Marco Abis</a> again, who was
the remote-local organizer of the conference, for making it happen. I 
met wonderful new people, and learned (or refined my understanding) of 
many topics!</p>
<p>During the coming days, I will be adding my session notes to the 
<a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/">conf wiki</a> coming days, and once I digested all the feedback I 
got during and outside the sessions, I will be writing up the <em>Tree 
Optimized Test Runner</em> and the <em>app-test DSLs to have multiple drivers
for a single TestCase</em> ideas in more detail.</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2013/09/30/citcon-turin-2013/">CITCON Turin 2013</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CITCON London 2011</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2011/11/citcon-london-2011.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 09:26:00 CET</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[citcon]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[conferences]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2011/11/citcon-london-2011.html</guid>
      <description>CITCON London 2011</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
<p>Given what a great conference <a href="/2010/11/my-citcon-london-2010-experience.html">CITCON 2010</a> was, when registration opened for <a href="http://citconf.com/london2011/">CITCON 2011</a>, I didn't hesitate - which turned out to be a good thing, since spots had filled up rather quick. So next year, watch the <a href="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/citcon/">mailing list</a>, and rush to the registration form!</p><br/><h2 id="friday_evening_-_open_spaces_introductiontopic_proposals">Friday Evening - Open Spaces Introduction/Topic Proposals</h2><br/><p>It was held at <a href="http://skillsmatter.co.uk">Skillsmatter</a>, so I assumed there will be no surprises for me there (great infrastructure), but since I didn't have to take the tube this time (picked my accommodation to be walking distance from Glasswell Road on purpose), I've quickly learned that <a href="http://maps.bing.com">Bing Maps</a> has little to no knowledge of Glasswell Road and Skillsmatter. So the first day I took a nice, leisurely, albeit somewhat longer road towards the location.</p><br/><p>The registration went flawlessly, ran by <a href="http://twitter.com/PaulJulius">PJ</a>'s mom. Great job!</p><br/><p><a href="http://twitter.com/PaulJulius">PJ</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/Jtf">Jeffery</a> made the introductions in their usual, entertaining manner. While it wasn't new for me, I was glad to see this time they emphasized that the schedule can change throughout the day - apparently it wasn't only me who had been surprised by it last year. And of course the schedule did change.</p><br/><p>Because <a href="http://twitter.com/builddoctor">Julian Simpson</a> couldn't make it, I introduced his topic (<a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Do_you_use_your_tests_in_prod">Do you use your tests in prod?</a>), and then two of my own - <a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=To_Feature_Branch_Or_Not_To_Feature_Branch">Continuous Release and Delivery in Downloadable Product Companies</a> and <a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Configuration_Changes">Why Most People Don't have a Rollback Plan for Releases and instead "plan" to Hack Forward</a>.</p><br/><p>The great thing about proposing topics is that even when it doesn't meet the threshold to have a whole session dedicated to it, a lot of people now know that you are interested in this topic, and find you to share their experiences about it during the breaks.</p><br/><p>To my surprise, we actually followed <a href="https://twitter.com/Jtf">Jeffery</a>'s recommendation and we didn't run side conversations during the proposals, so the process was smooth and efficient, and there was more than enough time to chat later - especially that I didn't worry much about the agenda, since proposing two topics made my priorities to attend those, and I knew that whatever agenda we'll have at Friday closing time is not final.</p><br/><p>As we learned the next day, when you propose a topic, you should be careful which words to use. In my case, rollback was a terrible word, since many interpreted as going back in time, undoing, while what I meant was more like backout (planned and disciplined retreat).</p><br/><h2 id="sessions_i_attended">Sessions I attended</h2><br/><p>I've added my notes on the <a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Main_Page#CITCON_Europe_2011_London">conference wiki</a>:</p><br/><ul><br/><li><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=To_Feature_Branch_Or_Not_To_Feature_Branch">Feature Branching, Feature toggles, What Makes a Build a Release</a></li><br/><li><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Configuration_Changes">Releases without things going wrong + why few make backout plans</a> </li><br/><li><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Do_you_use_your_tests_in_prod">Do you use your tests in prod</a></li><br/><li><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Organizational_Anthropology">Organizational Anthropology</a></li><br/></ul><br/><h2 id="sessions_i_wish_i_attended">Sessions I wish I attended</h2><br/><ul><br/><li><a href="http://www.thetestingplanet.com/2011/11/bitbeambot-the-angry-birds-playing-mobile-testing-robot/">BitbeamBot: The Angry Birds Playing, Mobile Testing Robot</a> by <a href="http://twitter.com/hugs">Jason Huggins</a> ran a session about automated UI testing of touch screens</li><br/><li>there was a TDD session - given that often I need (want) to explain TDD to people new to the concept, it would have been a great learning opportunity seeing someone (was it run by <a href="http://twitter.com/sf105">Steve Freeman</a>?) else's approach to introducing it. Plus likely I would have gained a new understanding of TDD... </li><br/><li>Backyard beekeeping - I ended up in a random chat, but I was would have been curious to see these non-technical, non-work related sessions</li><br/><li>I couldn't stay long enough in the <a href="http://www.theslaughteredlambpub.com/">Slaughtered Lamb</a></li><br/></ul><br/><h2 id="the_hallway_chats">The hallway chats</h2><br/><p>While open spaces are already like an unconference, nonetheless a lot of great conversations took place during the breaks (didn't get to use the law of two feet this time either), and I've met a lot of great people. I just wish I had more time to talk more with each of them. Guess I queued these conversations for future processing on twitter or via email. </p><br/><p>In contrast to last year's conference, I spent almost the whole time offline, in the analog world, and it didn't feel the least bit wrong. I've pretty much only used twitter when I followed someone on twitter - instead of exchanging emails or business card. Though I have to admit, business cards are great for jotting down small reminder notes on them.</p><br/><h2 id="some_travel_lessons_ive_learned">Some travel lessons I've learned</h2><br/><p>While this is tangential to CITCON, I have learnt a few lessons on this trip. I'll list them here, hoping it's beneficial for others.</p><br/><ul><br/><li>have your travel plans printed out (a'la <a href="http://tripit.com">TripIt</a>. It made the check-in process much smoother, and going from the airport to my hotel was perfectly relaxed, knowing exactly which tube to take. The only part I forgot to plan was from the Nueremberg Airport to the office (only remembered that would be useful when I landed). Thanks to <a href="http://www.manager-tools.com/2011/07/create-a-trip-folder">Career Tools</a> for the idea (and they great advice for attending conferences, approaching your boss about sending you to a conference, and more)!</li><br/><li>Phones, data plans, roaming. While this isn't the reason that I always buy my phones from the stores and not from the carriers, being able to just buy a prepaid SIM in London made a huge difference. It's not necessarily the money, though I think I've saved there (for the four days I stayed, just the data plan would have cost me 14 €, and there are the calls I made - contrast that with the £15), but rather that making a call or using mobile net wasn't something that I had to consciously  choose (is it worth the extra roaming charge?).</li><br/><li>have enough slack in your trip. I arrived Friday afternoon, and returned home on Monday morning. This allowed me to dedicate Friday and Saturday to the conference (and the Slaughtered Lamb afterwards), be able to meet up with friends living in London on Sunday, and the fact that some of my friends were an hour late just simply didn't cause a problem. And financially it doesn't have to be more expensive - I believe I spent about the same amount on the three nights' stay as I did last year for two nights. Advance planning, more research for accommodation helps you with that.</li><br/><li>If you need travel accessories (e.g.: AC adapter for the UK), try them before leaving home - I managed to buy adapters incompatible with my laptop's charger. Luckily the reception at my hotel managed to find one of theirs that was compatible, but it took a long five minutes for them to find one, so I wouldn't rely on this</li><br/><li>In addition to that, I forgot my phone charger at home, and while Bing Maps isn't perfect, it's much better than walking in London without a GPS. Lesson learned: it's handy when you have a USB cable with you that you can use to charge from somebody's laptop - the 10 cm long USB cable fits in any pocket.</li><br/></ul>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2011/11/citcon-london-2011.html">CITCON London 2011</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My #citcon London 2010 experience</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2010/11/my-citcon-london-2010-experience.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2010 20:07:00 CET</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[citcon]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[conferences]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2010/11/my-citcon-london-2010-experience.html</guid>
      <description>My #citcon London 2010 experience</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
<h1><span class="Apple-style-span"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-weight: normal; font-size: medium;">This was both my first </span></span><a href="http://citconf.com/london2010" style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-weight: normal; font-size: medium; ">citcon </a><span class="Apple-style-span"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-weight: normal; font-size: medium;">(apparently pronounced "kitcon") and open space conference I've attended, and I'm sure it hasn't been the last for either one!</span></span></h1><p style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: medium; ">The venue was the <a href="http://skillsmatter.com/">Skillsmatter Exchange</a>, which was simple in appearance (guess it's a former warehouse of sort), but with enough space, flipcharts, tables, projectors, seats needed for this event. There was enough space to chat without disturbing sessions, or to just grab a coffee - which seemed to be sufficient for this conference (and for my needs/expectations).</p><p style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: medium; ">Friday evening was dedicated for introductions and for session proposals, topic merging, voting, and of course, some beer. It was a nice reminder that my problems are not unique - I've actually stepped out from the proposals line given that a number people already suggested topics that covered my problem. Maybe it was more to do with the fact that I'm still not comfortable speaking in front of big audiences (more than 20-30 people make me nervous. Guess I'll just have to practice, given that there was a time when any public speaking used to scare me.).</p><p style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: medium; ">Saturday morning the schedule was supposedly finalized by the end of the breakfest provided. Later on it turned out not to be the case, so I've missed a couple of sessions, though all I've attended were great. Having a problem to choose from many good sessions is much better than not having any good ones to chose from. Nonetheless, I'll keep this in mind for future open spaces not to take anything granted unitl you are in the session.</p><p style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: medium; ">The first session was about <strong><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Database_testing_and_deployment">database testing, versioning, and deployment</a></strong>. This is a topic close and dear to my heart, and it was interesting to realize the bounderies of the boxes I've been thinking in - e.g.: I've not been working in multiversion deployment scenarios, where you need to go from any version to the current. I've also learned to be more explicit in my communication, e.g.: when I asked about a <a href="http://www.agitar.com/solutions/products/automated_junit_generation.html">tool like agitar's</a> for databases to generate characteristic tests for regression, just because a few people nodded that might be useful, I've assumed everyone knows what I'm talking about, which led to a misunderstanding between me and <a href="http://gojko.net/">Gojko Adzic</a> about testing with "random data". Though we've clarified this after the session, I'm wondering why it happened that I couldn't explain it during the session.</p><p style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: medium; ">Before lunch, I've attended the <strong><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Managing_Multiple_Dependencies">module dependency handling</a></strong> session, where I learned there is no tool yet for handling versioned dependencies (i.e.: I would want to know if the version/feature branches of a given project are compatible with all versions of dependant projects). The discussion was nice, but I've had some trouble following once things got Java specific.</p><p style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: medium; ">Next up was the <strong><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Overcoming_Organisational_Defensiveness">Overcoming Organisational Defensiveness</a></strong> session. I thought I knew a lot about this topic, and was pleasantly surprised by all the new aspects that I learned, including, but not limited to:</p><ul style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: medium; "><li>Don't fix your problem, fix their problem</li><li>while not everyone agrees, in certain contexts, un-branding a practice helps (e.g.: we referenced Dan North's example from another conference of not doing pair programming, but asking two people to look into a problem together)</li><li>when developers don't have time to improve, bringing in a coach doesn't solve the problem. You first need to dedicate time for them to learn.</li><li>instead of trying to change people, step back and see if you can create some change that would effect them in ways you would like, but doesn't require their prior approval/cooperation and you can do it yourself</li><li>don't just do 5 whys, do the 5 "so what?" too</li></ul><p style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: medium; "></p><p style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: medium; ">The next session's title was <strong><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Using_KPIs/Getting_a_data-driven_org.">Using KPIs/Getting a data-driven organization</a></strong>, however, the topic shifted to organization culture and psychology. Not suprisingly, we didn't find a silver bullet, but there were a number of good laughs and ideas (transparency, exposure, accountability, responsibility, over and undercontroling, ownership were the main themes). It was a smaller session, but in my experience that made it much more focused and interactive; contrasted with the bigger sessions. Plus I have been surprised, there are people using vim on the mac :)</p><p style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: medium; ">The final session was <strong><a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=Beyond_Basic_TDD">Beyond Basic TDD</a></strong>, where the essence boils down to TDD having a marketing message that design will just evolve, despite Kent Beck admitting that might not always be the case (i.e.: if you've got people with good design sense, no methodology will prevent them from writing well designed code). There should be more focus on teaching programmers about design. Gojko took over from there to facilitate the discussion around what can be done to bring those familiar with TDD basics to the next level, I have to admit I've become quite exhausted by this session, something to keep in mind next time when organizing sessions around a whiteboard.</p><p style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; font-size: medium; ">Overall, it was great fun, it was good to bounce ideas off from people, chat with random ones, and to talk with people known only from twitter. The one thing I regret is that I had to skip the after event pubbing (first evening I was just way too tired, while Saturday evening I was catching up with some friends living in London). Next time I'll try to allocate one more day for the trip, because the hallway conversations were great during the event, and I would be surprised if they were any worse in the pub. </p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2010/11/my-citcon-london-2010-experience.html">My #citcon London 2010 experience</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
