<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>Do. Reflect. Learn. Repeat!</title>
    <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</link>
    <description>Excercises in public learning</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 12:32:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>Facilitating the Global Day of Coderetreat Zagreb (and a little Nuremberg) 2015</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2015/11/15/facilitating-the-global-day-of-coderetreat-zagreb-and-a-little-nuremberg-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2015 12:30:00 CET</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[code retreat]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[community]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[facilitating]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[organizing]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">7Wh3mKRL5MoalaxX7WlvFFplBkw=</guid>
      <description>Facilitating the Global Day of Coderetreat Zagreb (and a little Nuremberg) 2015</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          <p>This was the second Zagreb <a href="http://coderetreat.org">coderetreat</a>, and this year we actually managed to
organize it to take place the same day as the rest of the world :) Thanks to 
the sponsors <a href="http://toptal.com">Toptal</a>, <a href="http://goodcode.io">Good Code</a>, <a href="http://floatingpoint.io">Floating Point</a> and
the hosts <a href="https://twitter.com/zeljkofilipin">Zeljko</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/maljosa">Aljosa</a> for making it happen!</p>
<p><img alt="the team working on the game of life" src="/img/gdcr2015zag/whole-team.jpg" /></p>
<p>Due to our last minute advertising, the participants were Ruby heavy, but 
still, the eight people coded in Ruby, Python, C#, Haskell, JavaScript, and
R throughout the day - quite a feat if you consider that two attendees were 
not professional programmers!</p>
<p>Due to a late start and time constraint we only had 5 sessions with the
following constraints:</p>
<ol>
<li>no extra constraints, just exploring pairing, TDD, 4 rules of simple design,
    and the game of life</li>
<li>evil ping pong pairing</li>
<li>void methods only + remote pairing with Nuremberg (Germany)</li>
<li>maximum 3 lines per method</li>
<li>no conditionals (later restricted to no booleans)</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="remote-pairing-with-nuremberg">Remote pairing with Nuremberg</h1>
<p><img alt="remote pairing from zagreb" src="/img/gdcr2015zag/remote02.jpg" /></p>
<p>As I've known <a href="https://twitter.com/marcoemmrich">Marco</a> from before, a few days before the GDCR we had 
a video call where we tested out the feasibility  of remote pairing (we've
tried <a href="http://tmate.io">tmate.io</a> and <a href="http://floobits.com">FlooBits</a>), and
deemed it feasible for a coderetreat (i.e.: can be set up during the lunchbreak).</p>
<p><em>Aside</em>: Planning is everything, but no plan survives first contact with 
the enemy. All pairs used <a href="http://teamviewer.com">TeamViewer</a>
and VisualStudio in the end.</p>
<p>We used the lunchbreak to pair people up using a direct videocall between
me and <a href="https://twitter.com/marcoemmrich">Marco</a>, but that is a cumbersome process and we'll try to
come up with a better one for next time (maybe use a Google spreadsheet
where each location can put down the interested parties' language, tooling
and communication preferences before?), but nonetheless all remote pairs 
reported having had fun!</p>
<p>Facilitating remote pairs is surprisingly easy, but only when the pairs use
the headphones which can be shared between two people - one bud in each person's
ear.</p>
<p>While it does require some prior coordination between the hosts (sync session 
start times, agree on the same constraint for the session, etc.), I do suggest
you try it out if you have the chance, especially if you haven't remote paired
before!</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2015/11/15/facilitating-the-global-day-of-coderetreat-zagreb-and-a-little-nuremberg-2015/">Facilitating the Global Day of Coderetreat Zagreb (and a little Nuremberg) 2015</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
