<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>Do. Reflect. Learn. Repeat!</title>
    <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</link>
    <description>Excercises in public learning</description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2013 05:31:46 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>Own your data (or why did I move away from Blogger and WordPress?)</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2013/08/04/own-your-data-or-why-did-i-move-away-from-blogger-and-wordpress/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2013 14:25:00 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[data]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[ownership]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">8UAjTLJV0td1NxR0DNBSZhVVots=</guid>
      <description>Own your data (or why did I move away from Blogger and WordPress?)</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This blog used to be two separate blogs, hosted at 
<a href="http://blogger.com">Blogger</a> and <a href="http://wordpress.com">WordPress.com</a>,
respectively. I've gone through some trouble to migrate their content,
hopefully without breaking urls to this <a href="http://blogofile.com">Blogofile</a> 
based setup. In the process, I have lost a considerable number of 
features and conveniences - so why did I do this?</p>
<h2 id="owning-my-data-and-platform">Owning my data and platform</h2>
<p>As the saying goes, there is no such thing as a free lunch (or put more
bluntly, if you are not paying for it, <em>you</em> are the product being 
sold). A prime example is <a href="http://wordpress.com">WordPress.com</a>, which reserves the
right to display ads on your freely hosted blog, while <a href="http://blogger.com">Blogger</a>
probably enhances their advertisement profile of you - I don't know.</p>
<p>Even if these platforms don't do anything bad at the moment, they can
pretty much change the features available to you, or any other aspects
of their terms of service - remember that story about the 
<a href="http://news.cnet.com/8301-1023_3-57560370-93/instagram-rolls-back-terms-of-service-after-ownership-dustup/">Instagram ToS change regarding commercial use of your photos</a>?
Sure, it turned out to be a misunderstanding and/or they backed down,
but theoretically they can do it.</p>
<p>Of course, this wasn't a concern when I started out with blogging, but 
certainly is something to consider now that I am nearing post #42. </p>
<p>These considerations are of course applicable for other service 
providers beyond blogging, e.g.:</p>
<ul>
<li>(sports) tracking applications - while I have not yet gotten around 
  to building up a website like <a href="http://www.susi-ralf.de/index.html">Suzi &amp; Ralf</a>, but I know 
  eventually I will want to create something with the trails of all the
  places I've been to, whether for fun or for an anniversary gift or
  similar - and most sites make it rather hard to export your data 
  conveniently (<a href="http://endomondo.com">endomondo</a> is particularly annoying, so I'm 
  real grateful for the easy zip-export of <a href="http://runkeeper.com">runkeeper</a>!)</li>
<li>social networks - does <a href="http://linkedin.com">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="http://facebook.com">Facebook</a>, 
  <a href="http://xing.com">Xing</a>, etc. allow you to easily export your contacts and their
  contact details? I would be pretty upset to find myself without a 
  personal copy of that data</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course, I keep using services hosted by others, but I try to make 
sure I use one with a friendly <a href="http://www.dataliberation.org/">data liberation</a>
policy!</p>
<h2 id="other-considerations">Other considerations</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>backup</strong> - sure, it's almost a repeat of the prior point, but worth 
  noting. It doesn't happen as often as before, but there is always the
  possibility of <a href="http://blog.theoldreader.com/post/56209408824/important-update">data loss or service outage</a></li>
<li><strong>version control</strong> - being a software developer, this is almost 
  second nature to me - it's incredibly liberating to be able to throw
  all my changes away and go back to a previous, known good version of
  a post draft.</li>
<li><strong>offline authoring</strong> - I do a lot of my writing and hobby coding 
  during my train commute, with spotty internet connection at best.
  Working locally on my laptop with my favorite text editor beats any
  online editor widget. </li>
<li><strong>full customizations</strong> - sure, probably there is a WordPress plugin
  for anything I would want to do, but for a lot of the small checks, 
  it takes longer to find, learn, and configure the one I need than
  to implement it in <a href="http://python.org">python</a> - e.g.: checking the site for
  broken links, custom reports, etc. I should probably mention the html
  template customizations here too, though you might be able to tell
  that is not yet the highest priority for me :)</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
