<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>Do. Reflect. Learn. Repeat!</title>
    <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</link>
    <description>Excercises in public learning</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2015 12:01:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>Podcasts I Listen To</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2014/03/19/podcasts-i-listen-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2014 08:30:00 CET</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[podcasts]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">LZVxlPekUBiw_pI1RaC0HDD6pkk=</guid>
      <description>Podcasts I Listen To</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          <p>Initially I started listening to podcasts to keep up with news in
the software development space, but it has expanded way beyond that.
Recently <a href="https://twitter.com/zeljkofilipin/status/444052979172507648">Zeljko has asked for podcast recommendations</a>,
so instead of shooting a private email I thought I would share the
casts I listen to publicly in a post.</p>
<p>Note it's a <em>long</em> list - but I don't hesitate to skip/delete an episode
based on its description or its first few minutes (caveat: some casts
by their structure are less exciting in the first few minutes).</p>
<p>I've grouped the list, but of course there are many of them that would
fit multiple categories - no taxonomy ever is perfect.</p>
<p>Hope you find something you'll like!</p>
<h2 id="software-development">Software Development</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://dotnetrocks.com/">.NET Rocks</a> was one of the first podcasts I've listened to. As the
  name suggests, it's focused on the Microsoft development space, but the hosts
  are critical enough when needed, and many episodes are tech agnostic. Disclaimer:
  I'm a happy owner of a .NET Rocks mug</li>
<li><a href="http://thetabletshow.com/">The Tablet Show</a> - the sister show to .NET Rocks, with focus on mobile
  and tablets. The Microsoft focus doesn't come through that heavily
  (though it's there)</li>
<li><a href="http://devopscafe.org/">DevOps Cafe</a> - there are some great interviews on here, though the format 
  (sound quality?) took me some getting used to. It exposes me to topics I'm
  a total n00b about, whether its security or networking.</li>
<li>
<p><a href="http://hanselminutes.com/">Hanselminutes</a> - Scott started this with the tagline "the podcast that doesn't
  waste your time". The episodes are limited to around half an hour, and while
  the topics stay around tech, they also touch on the social/human side, such as</p>
<ul>
<li>Scott interviewing his wife about how it is to live with a geek</li>
<li>interviews with developers from publicly underrepresented developer
  groups (women, world class climbers, you name it :)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="http://rubyrouges.com/">Ruby Rogues</a> - a panel discussion about things Ruby related, but many of
  the discussions are applicable to other programming languages, or at the very
  least inspire one to learn how the thing discussed works in the listener's 
  language. Add on top of this they bring up cultural topics that should be
  discussed in the software development community.</p>
</li>
<li><a href="http://javaposse.com/">The Java Posse</a> - it used to be a mix of panel discussion of java/scala programmers,
  and recordings of sessions from the yearly open spaces conferences of 
  the same name, but lately it's just the conference stuff. So great for learning, but
  I miss the chat shows.</li>
<li><a href="http://theshipshow.com/">The Ship Show</a> - build and release engineering, devops, and everything else in 
  between. Panel discussions, news and views, listener questions, as well as 
  interviews. It definitely fills a niche.</li>
<li><a href="http://cognitect.com/podcast">ThinkRelevance/CogniCast</a> - anything and everything related to Clojure or Datomic,
  produced professionally by the company where Rich Hickey works. Sometimes 
  it's too Clojure heavy for me (though you might find that a good thing), but it
  has blown my mind a few times.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="pop-science">(Pop-)Science</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00srz5b">A Brief History of Mathematics</a> - a former BBC Radio4 programme archived in podcast
  form. Short episodes on the various influential people in mathematics. I'm planning
  to re-listen to this series soon.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qshd">More or Less</a> - Statistical CSI :) Produced by (among others) Tim Harford, 
  this show takes a look at public statistical claims from any aspect of life, 
  and go after digging up sources for these claims as well as verifying them
  and the methodology used. Listener topic suggestions are encouraged!</li>
<li><a href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=127413729">NPR Planet Money</a> - Awesome economics podcast, with short and entertaining 
  episodes. They have provided the best economics coverage of the EU debt crisis
  for laymen like me.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="social-politics">Social, Politics</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/analysis">Analysis</a> - another BBC Radio 4 programme. Each episode presents one person's
  research and conclusion/opinion of a given topic. Expect lot of source 
  interviews.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b010q0n0">Four Thought</a> - personal speeches about personal experiences, delivered to a live
  audience, followed by a few questions and answers. It keeps reminding me how
  little I know about the world and people.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qk11">Moral Maze</a> - a panel hearing out witnesses on moral questions, arguing with
  the witnesses and with themselves, exploring different these difficult topics, which
  usually don't have clearcut answers. Great topics, great points, and some
  heated debate.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.npr.org/series/6263392/intelligence-squared-u-s">Intelligence Squared</a> - recording of live, superbly moderated debates, published
  as podcasts. The structure (uninterrupted opening statements, Q &amp; A, uninterrupted 
  closing statements, voting) is wonderful, and the moderator is on top of his game. The
  topics are timely and interesting, the debaters are amazingly authentic, and the
  voting results do show that people can change their minds.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.onbeing.org/">On Being with Krista Tippett</a> - exploring open and tolerant faith. Whether by interviewing
  atheists, the translator of the Dalai Lama, a marine biologist, civil right movement
  participants, or marketing guru Seth Godin. Superb audio quality and Krista does have
  a voice which in itself makes it worth listening to any episode - not to mention the
  positive thinking that radiates from the talks.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qy05">Thinking Allowed</a> - short BBC Radio4 programme reporting on recent papers or books
  in the field of sociology on various subjects.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="outdoors">Outdoors</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.theoutdoorsstation.co.uk/">The Outdoors Station</a> - an irregular podcast. I tend to skip the product episodes,
  and prefer the interview ones. While irregular, the archive does hold quite a 
  few gems - if you are into outdoor stories.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="business-chatting">Business, chatting</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.startupsfortherestofus.com/">Startups for the Rest Of Us</a> - if you ever wanted to understand how small software business 
  owners and marketers think, and need an occasional reminder that we as software
  people are there to deliver solutions, not to write software, it's a great one. On
  top of this, there is a bunch of practical advice if you are trying yourself out 
  in internet marketing. And you can follow Mike and Rob as they develop their respective
  businesses</li>
<li><a href="http://techzinglive.com/">techzing</a> - while lately it has become more of a weekly recorded talk of two friends, 
  which presents new listeners with a steep learning curve during the first few episodes,
  in the past they had wonderful interviews - and even now their hobbies are exciting
  and inspiring enough to listen to (have you ever considered coaching your children's
  school's math team? They actually do that).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="career">Career</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://manager-tools.com/">Career tools, Manager Tools</a> - I would say this is mandatory listening to anyone who
  wants to make progress in an enterprise environment. Especially if you want to 
  become an executive. Their advice is quite prescriptive (they are ex-military after
  all), but they present their reasoning in (sometimes too) much detail. </li>
<li><a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/category/podcasts/">Kalzumeus Software</a> - the once-in-a-rare-while podcast of Patrick McKenzie (a.k.a.: patio11).
  There is everything from living in Japan to superb advice to furthering your career,
  especially if you are a freelancer. Since there aren't too many episodes, you can go back 
  and listen to all of them!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="reference">Reference</h2>
<p>These casts I don't regularly listen to anymore, but have them
bookmarked in case I would want to dive deeper in the topics they
address, for the episodes I've listened to convinced me of its
quality.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://beingtheworst.com/">Being the Worst</a> - for event sourcing and Domain Driven Design</li>
<li><a href="http://marketingforfounders.com/">Marketing for Founders</a> - Feels like marketing 10x-20x lectures.
  Not super exciting to listen to if you don't do this, but probably
  superb to pick up the basic ideas fast.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="and-the-best-podcasts-theme-music-award-goes-to">And the Best Podcasts Theme Music Award Goes To...</h2>
<p>Hard to tell. Obviously, the Cognicast has the advantage that guests 
choose their own intro and exit music... So I have to disqualify it :)
From the rest, I can narrow it down to the Ruby Rogues and The Ship Show,
but not any further...</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2014/03/19/podcasts-i-listen-to/">Podcasts I Listen To</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Own your data (or why did I move away from Blogger and WordPress?)</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2013/08/04/own-your-data-or-why-did-i-move-away-from-blogger-and-wordpress/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2013 14:25:00 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[data]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[ownership]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">8UAjTLJV0td1NxR0DNBSZhVVots=</guid>
      <description>Own your data (or why did I move away from Blogger and WordPress?)</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          <p>This blog used to be two separate blogs, hosted at 
<a href="http://blogger.com">Blogger</a> and <a href="http://wordpress.com">WordPress.com</a>,
respectively. I've gone through some trouble to migrate their content,
hopefully without breaking urls to this <a href="http://blogofile.com">Blogofile</a> 
based setup. In the process, I have lost a considerable number of 
features and conveniences - so why did I do this?</p>
<h2 id="owning-my-data-and-platform">Owning my data and platform</h2>
<p>As the saying goes, there is no such thing as a free lunch (or put more
bluntly, if you are not paying for it, <em>you</em> are the product being 
sold). A prime example is <a href="http://wordpress.com">WordPress.com</a>, which reserves the
right to display ads on your freely hosted blog, while <a href="http://blogger.com">Blogger</a>
probably enhances their advertisement profile of you - I don't know.</p>
<p>Even if these platforms don't do anything bad at the moment, they can
pretty much change the features available to you, or any other aspects
of their terms of service - remember that story about the 
<a href="http://news.cnet.com/8301-1023_3-57560370-93/instagram-rolls-back-terms-of-service-after-ownership-dustup/">Instagram ToS change regarding commercial use of your photos</a>?
Sure, it turned out to be a misunderstanding and/or they backed down,
but theoretically they can do it.</p>
<p>Of course, this wasn't a concern when I started out with blogging, but 
certainly is something to consider now that I am nearing post #42. </p>
<p>These considerations are of course applicable for other service 
providers beyond blogging, e.g.:</p>
<ul>
<li>(sports) tracking applications - while I have not yet gotten around 
  to building up a website like <a href="http://www.susi-ralf.de/index.html">Suzi &amp; Ralf</a>, but I know 
  eventually I will want to create something with the trails of all the
  places I've been to, whether for fun or for an anniversary gift or
  similar - and most sites make it rather hard to export your data 
  conveniently (<a href="http://endomondo.com">endomondo</a> is particularly annoying, so I'm 
  real grateful for the easy zip-export of <a href="http://runkeeper.com">runkeeper</a>!)</li>
<li>social networks - does <a href="http://linkedin.com">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="http://facebook.com">Facebook</a>, 
  <a href="http://xing.com">Xing</a>, etc. allow you to easily export your contacts and their
  contact details? I would be pretty upset to find myself without a 
  personal copy of that data</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course, I keep using services hosted by others, but I try to make 
sure I use one with a friendly <a href="http://www.dataliberation.org/">data liberation</a>
policy!</p>
<h2 id="other-considerations">Other considerations</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>backup</strong> - sure, it's almost a repeat of the prior point, but worth 
  noting. It doesn't happen as often as before, but there is always the
  possibility of <a href="http://blog.theoldreader.com/post/56209408824/important-update">data loss or service outage</a></li>
<li><strong>version control</strong> - being a software developer, this is almost 
  second nature to me - it's incredibly liberating to be able to throw
  all my changes away and go back to a previous, known good version of
  a post draft.</li>
<li><strong>offline authoring</strong> - I do a lot of my writing and hobby coding 
  during my train commute, with spotty internet connection at best.
  Working locally on my laptop with my favorite text editor beats any
  online editor widget. </li>
<li><strong>full customizations</strong> - sure, probably there is a WordPress plugin
  for anything I would want to do, but for a lot of the small checks, 
  it takes longer to find, learn, and configure the one I need than
  to implement it in <a href="http://python.org">python</a> - e.g.: checking the site for
  broken links, custom reports, etc. I should probably mention the html
  template customizations here too, though you might be able to tell
  that is not yet the highest priority for me :)</li>
</ul>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2013/08/04/own-your-data-or-why-did-i-move-away-from-blogger-and-wordpress/">Own your data (or why did I move away from Blogger and WordPress?)</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Opening the 2013 paddling season on the Kocher</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2013/03/10/opening-the-2013-paddling-season-on-the-kocher/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2013 17:08:36 CET</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[canoe]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2013/03/10/opening-the-2013-paddling-season-on-the-kocher/</guid>
      <description>Opening the 2013 paddling season on the Kocher</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
I've just posted a brief description of our first trip of the season over at the <a href="http://www.songofthepaddle.co.uk/forum/showthread.php?40272-Opening-the-2013-season-on-the-Kocher-Braunsbach-to-K%FCnzelsau&amp;p=465323">Song of the Paddle</a> forum, check it out!
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2013/03/10/opening-the-2013-paddling-season-on-the-kocher/">Opening the 2013 paddling season on the Kocher</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First impressions of the Gumotex Palava inflatable canoe</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/06/14/first-impressions-of-the-gumotex-palava-inflatable-canoe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2012 18:25:37 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[palava]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[canoe]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[review]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[germany]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[gumotex]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[inflatable]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/06/14/first-impressions-of-the-gumotex-palava-inflatable-canoe/</guid>
      <description>First impressions of the Gumotex Palava inflatable canoe</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
<p>Our Palava arrived Friday the week before last, and since the weather was nice enough (warm, with patches of rain on Sunday), we immediately took it on a proper test ride on the Altmühl for the weekend, repeating an earlier trip we had on the same section of the river. Below I describe <em>why we chose</em> an inflatable, <em>how we chose</em> it, and <em>how it lived up to our expectations</em> (<a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/TL;DR" title="too long; didn’t read">tl;dr</a>: we like the boat).</p>
<p><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-52" height="225" src="/2012/06/after-first-inflated.jpg?w=300" title="The Gumotex Palava after we've first inflated it" width="300"/>
<h2></h2>
<h2>Why did we buy a funny looking inflatable canoe?</h2>
Guess after having a <a href="/2012/03/22/dahon-bullhead-with-aerobars/" title="Dahon Bullhead with Aerobars">folding bike</a> this is the next logical step (anyone knows about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Jetsons">Jetsons style folding cars</a>? :)) - just kidding...</p>
<p>While we have been canoeing for years, only moving to Germany made us think seriously about owning a canoe. The German canoe rental scene is rather different from what we were used to in Hungary, namely:
<ul>
<li>it requires more planning. You can't just decide in the morning that today you'd like to go paddling. Once we couldn't reserve a boat for the coming weekend on Thursday! Personalities aside (I've heard of people who like to plan their weekends in advance), even the weather forecast is not that reliable!</li>
<li>it's significantly more expensive. A two day canoe rental with transportation was €100 last year (varies with the vendor and the river, but a reasonable ballpark). Thus the <a href="http://www.gumotexboote.de/schlauchkanu-palava">Palava</a> (list price €629) pays for itself in seven weekends. In Hungary, the same ratio would be about 30-40 days of rental (ballpark figure).</li>
</ul>
Thus having our boat would financially makes sense (would pay for itself in the worst case in two seasons) and would give us freedom in our weekend/day off planning.
<h2>Choosing our canoe</h2>
We first considered a regular canoe, but quickly dismissed as being impractical for two people without a car (even with a car it's cumbersome and involves and additional train/bus ride to fetch the car from the start and then drive back down for the boat, potentially with one person waiting there). And if one didn't have a garage/garden, storage would be an extra problem.</p>
<p>Folding boats were also out of the question. A friend of mine has a folding kayak, and we didn't have a good experience with it: it is too heavy, takes up too much space to be carried without a car (and the actual design of the boat was too low seated, and thus it wasn't comfortable to paddle).</p>
<p>Inflatable kayaks - while they are cheaper and there are many models to choose from - were not an option either, since my girlfriend doesn't like kayaking :). Thus we were looking at inflatable canoes - fewer (<a href="http://www.grabner-sports.at/ADVENTURE-SL.adventuresl_x.0.html?&amp;L=2">Grabner</a> was the only other alternative we have found) and more expensive (guess the smaller market/demand explains it) choices. Thus we settled on the <a href="http://www.gumotexboote.cz/">Gumatex</a> brand.
<h2>Pre-Purchase Tests</h2>
Last year we met a retired couple who had a Palava, and they were kind enough to let us try it out (thanks again!). We concluded that it is a usable boat - and it's durable (they had it for about 10 years, only problem is now it has to be pumped a bit each day, while in the past it could go for days without). However, initially we were looking at the <a href="http://www.gumotexboote.de/schlauchkanu-scout">Scout</a>, for having a proper canoe shape. But it was pretty pricey for a blind purchase, thus we were searching for a way to try it out.</p>
<p>We found the opportunity by accident. The nice people at <a href="http://www.sport-schmidt-gmbh.de/">Sport Schmidt in Friedriechshafen</a> organized a test day in May, so we visited Lake Constance just for this occasion. Since it was there, we also tried the <a href="http://www.gumotexboote.de/schlauchraft-und-boot-baraka">Baraka</a>, but that is more suited for whitewater than the normal rivers we had in mind, so only the Palava is compared below with the Scout.
<ul>
<li><em>paddling comfort</em>: we kept rubbing our hands against the side of the Scout, which isn't pleasant. It might not be a problem for all - we are not tall (165/175 cms), and we have an unusual rear paddling style (normally I don't use the back seat of the canoe, but sit on the deck behind it - it provides a better line of sight and makes it easier to turn the boat. Maybe one gets used to it over time though, but the Palava - being much closer to the water - was a much more comfortable experience</li>
<li><em>turning</em>: compared to a solid canoe, both models turn crazy fast and easy - almost like a short kayak</li>
<li><em>going straight</em>: the Scout keeps direction almost like a normal canoe, but since I did two years whitewater kayaking and we have been canoeing for about 14 years, the Palava's ability is good enough for us</li>
<li><em>space</em>: the Scout has more of it, both for people and for luggage, however, even the Palava has enough for two people and gear (we had the bags we brought for the weekend for the test, with sleeping mats and bags, tent, dry/warm clothes, etc.), and we were comfortable and had space for even more bags (e.g.: two more backpacks would easily fit). We have seen pictures with two small kids and two parents without luggage in the Palava, but for touring (even longer ones, since the luggage for a week long trip is not much more than for a weekend trip) I'd say two people. The Scout is the family boat (or two Palavas :)</li>
<li><em>wind</em>: we couldn't test this, but we were somewhat concerned about how the Scout would handle wind, being light and being high out from the water. The Palava, with it's low height shouldn't be effected</li>
<li><em>weight</em>: both are light enough, so the hauling over dams and the like shouldn't be an issue. Plus with the many ropes on them, it's easy to move them alone.</li>
</ul>
In the end, we decided against the Scout. It's a great boat, but the Palava meets our needs, so the only two useful features of the Scout would be the shape and the straighter path. These are nice to have, but together with paddling discomfort we didn't feel paying almost double would be worth it.
<h2>The two days on the Altmühl &amp; impressions of the boat</h2>
This river doesn't really flow, and there are many dams that require hauling the boat (5 on the Treuchtlingen - Dollnstein (29km) and 3-4 on the Dollnstein-Eichstät (17km) section).</p>
<p>Putting the boat together is quick (<a href="http://www.gumotexboote.de/doppelhub-einhub-handpumpe-super-6-3">3L double chamber pump</a>) and intuitive, even when doing it for the first time. I wish the included bayonet-valve pump adapter had a loop (so we could secure it with a rope to the boat), but that's my only (and minor) complaint. One thing we should have purchased is a pressure gauge, but I expect we'll quickly get a feel for the right pressure. While talking about pumps: we've met a family with a <a href="http://www.sevylor-europe.com/p-73-hudson.aspx">Sevylor Hudson</a>, who were rather happy we had a pump they could use - they left theirs in the car, and the kayak somehow leaked air. Good reminder to always carry the pump in the boat!</p>
<p>Comparing the two Treuchtlingen - Eichstät trips (here is <a href="http://www.everytrail.com/view_trip.php?trip_id=1264633">last year's log with a rented canoe</a> and here is <a href="http://www.everytrail.com/view_trip.php?trip_id=1624079">this trip's</a>), with the inflatable - to our surprise - we ended up being faster by about half an hour (5.5 vs 6 &amp; 3.5 vs 4 hours) both days (even though last year it was raining heavily, so we were quite motivated). We assume it's because of the hauling - getting out, picking up the boat's backpack (about 80L drybag, which fits our 60L backpack and more easily), getting the boat out (beware: leaning forward with an 80L backpack is going to impact your balance :)), walking, putting it back on the water is essentially a non-operation, almost like just walking a bit to stretch your legs. And of course, we were familiar with the river already, so there were no navigation problems.</p>
<p>Paddling in the rear is somewhat harder - I did expect sour muscles in my back for the first canoeing of the year, but I was shocked to learn about the aching upper arm while attempting to drink a pint :) The boat turns quickly if you miss a beat or two, and thus much more corrections were needed. Also, I didn't have my custom made (by <a href="http://denescanoe.hu/">Denes Canoe</a>) paddle with me, and the standard size was just a bit too long for me in this boat.</p>
<p>Supposedly one should be on the knees in this boat, with support from the seat, but I've got bad knees and I anyway I need to switch positions in a normal canoe too, luckily, it's possible to sit normally too (though that's when you need a shorter paddle or get the sour muscles in the arm - or at least I did and suspect the normal sitting position is a contributor). The classic position (thighs almost horizontal, shins vertical) is unattainable, but not bad. My girlfriend felt totally comfy in the front, so it might be just me.</p>
<p>The ears have to be retrained, for the noises the boat makes when its scraping the bottom or a rock, but really few times does it do that - my non-scientific impression is that it copes well with really shallow water.</p>
<p>The backpack that comes with the boat is OK, but carrying the 22 kg over longer distances is no fun (but not a horrible experience either). There is no padding and chest/waist straps, which I missed - I've been spoiled by the <a href="http://over-board.co.uk/backpacks/waterproof-backpacks.html">great waterproof backpacks from OverBoard</a>. However, it's a solid waterproof bag. I wish it had reflective stripes on it, since we leave early/arrive late with the train, and thus for the walk it'd be useful. The bag is bigger than strictly needed, so both of our three piece paddles could be comfortably packed there too. The pump doesn't fit in however, and there isn't a proper external attachment point for it. But the boat is perfectly transportable, and we are really happy about it!</p>
<p>Packing away the boat takes about as long as a tent (plus the time required to clean it - and unless you had the time to properly dry it, it's worth drying it at home too).</p>
<p>In the end, the Palava met all our expectations - we had a great weekend canoeing!</p>
<hr><ol>
<li id="1">
    <strong><a href="">Rob Klaassen</strong></a> on <em>2012/11/27 11:02:12</em>: Yes, I've the same experience with the Palava in Norway, it`s great with 2+kid too (in his own inflatable chair!) and for 2 with a lot of luggage. Did you know its very durable cause it was developped for the army in Tjechie? Regards, Rob
</li><li id="2">
    <strong><a href="/category/outdoors/">zsepi</strong></a> on <em>2012/11/27 11:41:58</em>: Hey Rob,

thanks for confirming it accommodates a child as well - though I guess that wasn't what the military designers originally had in mind :)

Cheers,

Peter
</li><li id="3">
    <strong><a href="">Dan</strong></a> on <em>2013/07/06 16:00:12</em>: Great to read the above. Just ordered our Palava and it will arrive soon hopefully. We just had the same thoughts about spontaneous renting and storage problems, even though we have an own garage. Also the weight and complicated transportation of a regular canoe on the cars roof made the decission easy. After your report we are really excited to discover the palava on our own soon!
</li><li id="4">
    <strong><a href="/category/outdoors/">zsepi</strong></a> on <em>2013/07/08 09:22:58</em>: Dan, thanks for letting me know – I’m glad sharing my experience and thought process helped! Have fun with the new boat!
</ol>

          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/06/14/first-impressions-of-the-gumotex-palava-inflatable-canoe/">First impressions of the Gumotex Palava inflatable canoe</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Day 9: From Nagymaros to Budapest</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/05/02/day-9-from-nagymaros-to-budapest/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2012 06:52:18 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/05/02/day-9-from-nagymaros-to-budapest/</guid>
      <description>Day 9: From Nagymaros to Budapest</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
<p>Given that my current hosts didn't have other arrangements, a trip record was born - after a leisurely breakfast, cycling begun only after noon :)</p>
<p>One of my hosts decided that since she had to come to Budapest anyway, she might as well just bike instead of taking the train - thus I had company and the day's profile turned into a weekend cycling chat.</p>
<p>The weather was superb, and the cycling roads were quite crowded, but given the circumstances, it didn't bother me at all. With regards to the road quality - it isn't a smooth road, but has no cars, and the view is great. After Dunakeszi the road actually disappears (you should take the ferry to the right bank, there it continues), but having cycled this section many times I knew the back ways so we didn't have to take the #2 main road.</p>
<p>And then all of a sudden I was back in our flat in Budapest :)</p>
<p>It was 50 km with a net cycling time of 3:05 (h:mi). The gross time, of course, was much longer, but the ice cream break &amp; co. were essential and couldn't have been skipped :)</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/05/02/day-9-from-nagymaros-to-budapest/">Day 9: From Nagymaros to Budapest</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Day 8: From Gyor to Nagymaros</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/22/day-8-from-gyor-to-nagymaros/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2012 07:36:19 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/22/day-8-from-gyor-to-nagymaros/</guid>
      <description>Day 8: From Gyor to Nagymaros</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
<p>Managed to get an early start today, since my hosts had to leave around eight, and I preferred to be on the outside of the closed door (though they said I was free to choose...). After getting some munchies/bars/fruit for the day I was on the Eurovelo - again, which I promptly lost after leaving the inner city, but it goes along the car route 81 towards Tata. Actually, soon after getting out of the city, it goes on the road, and since it leads by the industrial district, there are tenwheeler trucks and lorries, and few signs.</p>
<p>Some kilometers before reaching Babolna, the Eurovelo takes a left to Nagyszentjanos, on a bad road, and in the village takes a right just before the railway crossing to a dirt road, seemingly only traveled (and travelable by) agricultural and offroad vehicles. I made the mistake of turning back and following the paved road, hoping to take the next right to Acs/Komarom, but there I was greeted with a traffic sign forbidding cyclists from the road - there and back an 8 km detour. So the dirt road. Incredibly slow and frustrating, but only lasts a few km and then a paved (though old and abandoned, and thus potholed) road emerges towards Acs. In the village center in the T-crossing take the left (there is an eurovelo sign, but not easy to find, and after the rails go to the right - just follow the signs for Komarom for the cars. Beware: high traffic road!</p>
<p>From here the signs are rare, but positioned at strategic locations, for some reason in the villages cyclist are forced off the road (which they rejoin just outside the village), which is painful with bags, since many of the forced alternatives are badly converted pedestrian roads, and there often isn't even a ramp at the crossing.</p>
<p>The car roads taken in order: 1, 117, 10, 11, mostly with traffic (there is one quality section road after Nyergesujfalu). The eurovelo crosses the danube at Pilismarot to Szob with a ferry (this time there was one every hour), but I continued to Visegrad on the 11, 'coz I haven't done this section of the road yet and because the friends I was staying that evening live in Nagymaros, with a ferry connection from Visegrad. Getting the bike up to their house in the hill was the most tiring!</p>
<p>Overall it was 141km in 6:40 (7:15). The road is ok if you can handle traffic, but otherwise (or with kids) I would suggest an alternative (maybe on the Slovakian side of the river) till Szob (visit Esztergom for sightseeing from Sturovo via the bridge), where the road is dedicated for cyclists, protected from car traffic (and has a great sight).</p>
<p>And probably was it not for catching up with friends I would have been in Budapest before daylight was out!</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/22/day-8-from-gyor-to-nagymaros/">Day 8: From Gyor to Nagymaros</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Day 7: From Vienna to Gyor</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/22/da-7-from-vienna-to-gyor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2012 07:11:44 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/22/da-7-from-vienna-to-gyor/</guid>
      <description>Day 7: From Vienna to Gyor</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
<p>As indicated, my breakfast-addiction have developed, so just about a kilometer from the camping's entrance I had to stop for eating some eggs at Toni's...</p>
<p>The road from here to Bratislava is an old acquaintance, the surprises were that this time i didn't have to take a detour, but could cycle through oil-refinery in Lobau, which meant no dirt roads and was appreciated. The other thing was that this was the time I cycled this stretch alone, and have to say that the last 15-20 km straight road to Hainburg is a trying alone. There was headwind, but there always is on this section, so no problems there... Except that this time there were cyclist coming from the other direction, and they had backwind!</p>
<p>After reaching Bratislava, the usual can't-find-my-way-out-of-the-city begun, and the road signs have been underutilized so to speak, but people were helpful and many spoke German (lot of them even better than I do :), so I got out. Essentially, if you want to continue the Donauradweg, after reaching the first bridge just keep following the road straight ahead, with its turns, and after some time you reach the recreational area, where there are two roads, one up on the flood defense hills (whatever they are called), the other below, on the side away from the river. After two or three Imbisses chose the lower one since there I know there is a sign at the end of it (where the poles are preventing cars entering) saying Rajka - that's the first village in Hungary.</p>
<p>Take that road for four kilometers, and when you see a sign to the left advertising and adventure park, take the left - in this direction the sign is missing, and if you go further you reach a main Slovakian road with lots of traffic (though I saw people take that, but I rather turned back from there).</p>
<p>From here on, both the road and the sign quality drops significantly, and even the EuroVelo 6 makes a lot of detours, e.g.: after reaching Bezenye, it takes a right and you reach Mosonmagyarovar after going through Hegyeshalom (take a left on the main road, even though there are no signs) confusing, given the same road you took from Rajka to Bezenye continues straight to Mosonmagyarovar...</p>
<p>The cycling road is being built, so you have to go with the traffic, and the driving culture is really different here - with a bicycle you are treated as a second class citizen of the road, so be prepared to a lot of cars taking you over without giving you much side distance, and even not giving you the right of way when they should, e.g.: at pedestrian/cyclist crossings in towns, or when they do they might shout at you (it only happened the next day for me). It's inconvenient, but I only had to refresh my muscle memory - I have been cycling in Hungary for years...</p>
<p>In Hegyeshalom I waited for my friend to join me for the section to Gyor (I was staying at his place), and the we got lost together and cycled to the Bahnhof club/restaurant on the local beach for dinner (it's *not* at the railway station!).</p>
<p>The roads were pretty bad, with an occasional good section (the Slovakian road leading out from Bratislava - aside from the lack of signs - is awesome smooth &amp; flat!), but the weather was great (I have a sunburnt left ear to show :(). The sad part was that you really didn't see much of the Danube on this section...</p>

          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/22/da-7-from-vienna-to-gyor/">Day 7: From Vienna to Gyor</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Day 6: From Ybbs to Vienna</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/20/day-6-from-ybbs-to-vienna/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2012 09:00:46 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/20/day-6-from-ybbs-to-vienna/</guid>
      <description>Day 6: From Ybbs to Vienna</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
<p>One good thing about staying at an Inn overnight id the breakfast: there is plenty!</p>
<p>There were two other cycling parties at the Inn, either it is that Austrians are sportier, or simply I was the only one who didn't get the memo about the start of the good weather and by now the German section is already full with touring people.</p>
<p>Personal record: managed to take the wrong turn just about 2.5kms after start :)</p>
<p>The road to Melk, then Kremms is pretty, leading through small villages among grapefields, and since we've cycled here 3 years ago, memories were popping up almost everywhere. Though on the flip side I was dreading the section where my tire exploded back than. And no, I am not superstitious :)</p>
<p>Here have I met the oldest cyclist of the tour - he already had shaking hand, but was going full straight when cycling. Sheldon Brown came to mind.</p>
<p>After Kremms finding the way to the bridge was a bit difficult again, and now came a boring, shaky section along the Danube - you know the kind of road that has thin cracks across its whole width every 10-15 meters? One can still do a decent speed, but it is definitely not pleasant...</p>
<p>Tulln surprised me with its logo for the Garden festival - says a lot about me that on seeing a bleu-green small 'g' all I can think is Google...</p>
<p>Unlike last time, I crossed to the left bank at the power plant before Vienna, remembering how bad the road was last time. And I can definitely suggest to enter Vienna on the left - pretty cool.</p>
<p>One problem though is that it's easy to loose the Radweg signs, but it doesn't hurt - just keep going along the Neues Donau (New Danube). The bigger issue though is that the camping is not marked anywhere, and locals of course have no clue where campings are. When asking for directions, ask about Ölhaus and Lobau (but don't go all the way to Lobau!). If you see Toni's Inselgrill, turn back and take the first exit to the right, cross the road at the pedestrians crossing, and go up the hill (there arwe signs for the cars).</p>
<p>Anyhow, that was 156 km in about 7:20. Now on to Gyôr (just finished breakfast at Toni's).</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/20/day-6-from-ybbs-to-vienna/">Day 6: From Ybbs to Vienna</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Day 5: From Engelhartzell to Ybbs</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/19/day-5-from-engelhartzell-to-ybbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2012 07:54:54 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/19/day-5-from-engelhartzell-to-ybbs/</guid>
      <description>Day 5: From Engelhartzell to Ybbs</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
<p>Or a sunny day on the austrian bicycle super highway. I had this kind of road quality in mind when I originally planned the trip :)</p>
<p>I won't even talk about the morning, suffice to say I was already pedaling at 10 :)</p>
<p>Apparently on the right side the cycling road goes together with the cars, so at the first possibility I crossed the river, and then was speeding (26km/h feels so when you have so much extra weight) downriver. It was sunny, but not yet warm, on wonderful flat, asphalted roads. Soon I had to ferry across (oh, and met a light touring couple) which - especially in the Donaschlingen - is definitely fun, it's probably one of the best views on the Danube (we actually camped here 4 years ago).</p>
<p>I sped on, only taking a break before Aschach: the little bridges over the creeks joining the Danube were cleaned, so there were no obstacles underneath. And the appropriate tool for it is a lorry carrying an excavator beak (?). Using that, it takes a water from the Danube, and simply drops it upbridge into the creek, creating such a strong current it cleans out everything from under the bridge. And I had to stop since the big lorry blocked the entire bridge :)</p>
<p>Aschach (which didn't yet have all the cruising ships with tourists, so getting through the town was easy now), then to Linz.</p>
<p>Of course, there was another ferry, but I am getting used to zigzagging between the two banks by now.</p>
<p>The last seven kilometers before Linz must be the least attractive section of the trip: just going on the cycling road next to a high traffic road, and some warehouses/industrial buildings to the right, and houses on the left (and thus so many crossings you can't ride at a decent speed).</p>
<p>The park the road leads out from Linz is still beautiful, pedestrians and riders separated meaningfully that fits both needs and allows peaceful coexistence. There is a bit more work that could be done to increase cooperation between road and touring cyclist (you really think it's OK to yell at me to stop with my bags on an incline just so the two of you can cruise by side by side instead of one of you falling behind the other to give me space?!).</p>
<p>What follows from here is the road biker's dream: superb asphalt, no traffic, flat, next to the Danube. Granted, if one does a normal touring speed, it might be rather boring, but leaning into the aerobars and just speeding it was fun!</p>
<p>And as usually happens, I enjoyed going fast so much that I stopped thinking, and when the road led me up on the powerplant to the other side I had a nagging idea that this might not be the best idea, and it'll mean I'll have to take another ferry (tax on my stupidity?), but shrugged it off and kept going.</p>
<p>A guy on a mountainbike took me over (I never understood why someone would cycle road on these tires), but I was surprised that just in 8 kms I had to pass him. Hope he understands it isn't about showing off, but I just always go at the speed that feels comfortable and that by the next day I'll have to be in Vienna...</p>
<p>When I got to the ferry it turned out it doesn't go until May, so instead of waiting, I took off across the haven, following the main road, and at some point I found a cycling road crossing that main road (R7, and the crossing has a brown house to the left), which I followed. After not taking the forget-which-tal radweg but going up and across the bridge, I saw the sign "#6 - zum Donauradweg sign", so I was relieved. Going across now the industrial zone made the section before Linz look beautiful, but there was a petrol station where I could refill my waterbottle, so all is well.</p>
<p>And I did eventually get to the Donauradweg/#6, and got to Ybbs on the right side. The last 12kms the road is bumpy, but has little traffic.</p>
<p>While my map claimed a camping here, according to the information table the nearest one is in Granz, 9 km away, and I felt that the 165km was rnough for today, so Gasthof it is for today.</p>
<p>The restaurant reminded me of Hungary. There is Cordon Blue on the menu, the liver dumpling soup is a bit too fatty for my taste - just like in many Hungarian restaurants :)</p>
<p>And here the heating was functioning correctly, and the owner actually took one of my backpacks up to my room :)</p>
<p>Tomorrow: to Vienna!</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/19/day-5-from-engelhartzell-to-ybbs/">Day 5: From Engelhartzell to Ybbs</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Day 4: From Straubing to Engelhartszell</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/18/day-4-from-straubing-to-engelhartszell/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2012 08:07:00 CEST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[outdoors]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/18/day-4-from-straubing-to-engelhartszell/</guid>
      <description>Day 4: From Straubing to Engelhartszell</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
<p>I forgot the cleaning rag I used to dry the bottom of the tent at Neustadt, but while it's tempting to blame the late start on the extra drying time, it doesn't seem to be realistic. Let's just accept that I am unable to leave any campsite before ten.</p>
<p>The nearby Aldi doesn't sell anything in the quantities I need, so even the smallest fruit packs will last at least two days. Makes packing a bit more difficult, but well.</p>
<p>The road leads through either normal roads with virtually no traffic, or asphalted cycling paths, so for most of the day I averaged around 20 km/h. Having my backpack on the panniers too definitely slowed, but not having it on my backpack is priceless!</p>
<p>I met the first other touring cyclist today, coming in the opposite direction.</p>
<p>The weather had lots of sun, but of course it was still a bit cold, and it often got cloudy.</p>
<p>There were many crossroads where almost all options were marked as Donauradweg, so I'm sure that there could have been shortcuts, but only in Deggendorf was there a local cyclist (retired, doesn't do mounting biking for the last four years, only touring due to heart problems - otherwise he looks impressively fit, wanna be like that) who guided me through the city.</p>
<p>I pretty much blindly followed the road signs, and there were no problems, except that just 15km before Passau it turned out that I should have already crossed to the other side of the river, but I was too happy speeding. And occasionally stopping, when the view prompted me like. Like with the deer behind the fence. In addition, a small girl was busy gathering grass and feeding it to them through the fence :)</p>
<p>Luckily, the cycling road led to a ferry, which was already operational, so I crossed the danube in sunshine.</p>
<p>The last 15 kms before Passau had everything I hated in the roads before: gravel, dirt, mud, and climbs (ok, not many potholes), so I was quite happy. I chose to leave Passau on the right side of the Danube, which led me through narrow (and I mean it, passing another bicycle was out of the question, and pedestrians had to stand sideways to give us way) roads, and the had a nice, asphalt roads till the border, and for most of the remaining section till Engelshartzell.</p>
<p>Where the camping, which is supposedly "open from the middle of April" was closed - guess we do the math differently. Will call next time. The youth hostel is also closed, so I end up in a family pension. Old house, cold room. I turned all thermostats to max, and left for dinner after shower (at least there was warm water).</p>
<p>There isn't much choice, so I went into the first pizzeria I have found. It was surprisingly good, and there was a great cozy feeling to it - only me, the waiter, the chef and a friend of theirs (who is still learning German). I enjoyed their chatter.</p>
<p>When I got back to the room, it was still cold, so I called up the owner - turns out she forgot to turn something on. Duh! In theory, I should have a nice warm room in an hour.</p>
<p>Of course I didn't, but usually I sleep in a tent, so no big problems, though I am still upset.</p>
<p>Matters are worst in the morning: still cold, and while the breakfast table is ready, no sign of tea or coffee, and nobody is in sight at 8. And the breakfast is sliced meat/cheese/jam with bread and rolls. Not impressed, don't know why I was expecting scrambled eggs and the like.</p>
<p>Anyhow, I rode 130km in 6h 50mi (8h 30mi), and had a roof above my head for the night. Clothes haven't dried, but eh. Now I should push today and tomorrow, while the good weather lasts!</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/04/18/day-4-from-straubing-to-engelhartszell/">Day 4: From Straubing to Engelhartszell</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
