<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>Do. Reflect. Learn. Repeat!</title>
    <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</link>
    <description>Excercises in public learning</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 12:41:30 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>The Power of (Open Source) Blueprints</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2015/12/05/the-power-of-open-source-blueprints/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2015 13:41:00 CET</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[change]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[citcon]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[coderetreat]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[community]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[organizing]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[teaching]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">TmQscoJEA-SD6hw3sIe4T-DcJt4=</guid>
      <description>The Power of (Open Source) Blueprints</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          <h2 id="what-are-blueprints">What are blueprints</h2>
<p>As per Wikipedia, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blueprint">blueprint</a> is something that <em>allowed
rapid and accurate reproduction of documents</em>. I have heard it used (and
used myself) for processes too.</p>
<p>They are powerful because they allow me or anyone else to recreate
someone else's tried and tested idea, which in turn allows the idea
to spread (scale) to unimaginable numbers and reach places (and provide
benefits to) the original inventor could have never dreamed of.</p>
<p>It allows a complete novice to the field to organize a successful event.
Think of it like a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franchising">franchise</a>. You yourself do put in the
work, and your success benefits the franchise as well as yourself.
However, you don't have to start from scratch; you have a process you
follow, that has been proven to work. When advertising your event, there
is the social proof that the brand exists that makes it easier to sell
it.</p>
<h2 id="examples">Examples</h2>
<p>Some such blueprints I've come across and worked with are</p>
<ul>
<li>the <a href="http://citconf.com/">CITCON</a> meta wiki about <a href="http://citconf.com/wiki/index.php?title=ConferencePlanning">organizing the open space
  conference</a> - and <a href="http://citconf.com/archive/budapest2012//">CITCON Budapest</a> was
  quite a success, which I couldn't have pulled off without having
  the process to follow</li>
<li><a href="http://coderetreat.org/">Coderetreats</a> - I've participated and facilitated in
  public &amp; firm-internal events. The educational sessions and the superb
  detailed documentation the coderetreat community provides make it
  almost too easy to run such an event - no surprise that in 2015 there
  were <a href="http://coderetreat.org/events/event/listByType?type=gdcr15">at least 158 events</a> on a single day!</li>
<li><a href="https://djangogirls.org/">Django Girls</a> - it started in June 2014 in Berlin, and
  by now it already took place on all continents - simply because they 
  have a wonderfully detailed tutorial on how to organize such an event!</li>
<li>the <a href="http://alistair.cockburn.us/Elephant+carpaccio">Elephant Carpaccio</a> also has a super detailed
  <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TCuuu-8Mm14oxsOnlk8DqfZAA1cvtYu9WGv67Yj_sSk/pub">facilitation guide</a></li>
</ul>
<p>... but I'm sure there are many more out there.</p>
<h2 id="benefits">Benefits</h2>
<p>If you are trying to bring change in your company/team, but you haven't
done it before, you don't have to necessarily invent workshops yourself
(of course, if you want, you can), but can simply take off established
ones "from the shelf".</p>
<p><em>Caution</em>: while you could theoretically run an event just from the
tutorials, it might be beneficial to have attended such a workshop
before running it. I've cooked my first <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paella"><em>paella</em></a> from a 
cookbook, without ever having eaten one before. While everyone agreed
I've cooked something delicious, later we had to acknowledge it had 
little to do with a real paella :)</p>
<h2 id="if-you-are-already-organizing-something">If you are already organizing something</h2>
<p>If you can afford it, I highly suggest you publicly document it (and
license it openly), so others have a chance to do the same. E.g.: many
user groups struggle finding speakers or sponsors - it would be great to
have a handbook on your sponsor/speaker attraction tactics. It won't
take away from the success of your event or the benefits to your
reputation, you simply just enable more people elsewhere to do the same!</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2015/12/05/the-power-of-open-source-blueprints/">The Power of (Open Source) Blueprints</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Facilitating the Global Day of Coderetreat Zagreb (and a little Nuremberg) 2015</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2015/11/15/facilitating-the-global-day-of-coderetreat-zagreb-and-a-little-nuremberg-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2015 12:30:00 CET</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[code retreat]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[community]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[facilitating]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[organizing]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">7Wh3mKRL5MoalaxX7WlvFFplBkw=</guid>
      <description>Facilitating the Global Day of Coderetreat Zagreb (and a little Nuremberg) 2015</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          <p>This was the second Zagreb <a href="http://coderetreat.org">coderetreat</a>, and this year we actually managed to
organize it to take place the same day as the rest of the world :) Thanks to 
the sponsors <a href="http://toptal.com">Toptal</a>, <a href="http://goodcode.io">Good Code</a>, <a href="http://floatingpoint.io">Floating Point</a> and
the hosts <a href="https://twitter.com/zeljkofilipin">Zeljko</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/maljosa">Aljosa</a> for making it happen!</p>
<p><img alt="the team working on the game of life" src="/img/gdcr2015zag/whole-team.jpg" /></p>
<p>Due to our last minute advertising, the participants were Ruby heavy, but 
still, the eight people coded in Ruby, Python, C#, Haskell, JavaScript, and
R throughout the day - quite a feat if you consider that two attendees were 
not professional programmers!</p>
<p>Due to a late start and time constraint we only had 5 sessions with the
following constraints:</p>
<ol>
<li>no extra constraints, just exploring pairing, TDD, 4 rules of simple design,
    and the game of life</li>
<li>evil ping pong pairing</li>
<li>void methods only + remote pairing with Nuremberg (Germany)</li>
<li>maximum 3 lines per method</li>
<li>no conditionals (later restricted to no booleans)</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="remote-pairing-with-nuremberg">Remote pairing with Nuremberg</h1>
<p><img alt="remote pairing from zagreb" src="/img/gdcr2015zag/remote02.jpg" /></p>
<p>As I've known <a href="https://twitter.com/marcoemmrich">Marco</a> from before, a few days before the GDCR we had 
a video call where we tested out the feasibility  of remote pairing (we've
tried <a href="http://tmate.io">tmate.io</a> and <a href="http://floobits.com">FlooBits</a>), and
deemed it feasible for a coderetreat (i.e.: can be set up during the lunchbreak).</p>
<p><em>Aside</em>: Planning is everything, but no plan survives first contact with 
the enemy. All pairs used <a href="http://teamviewer.com">TeamViewer</a>
and VisualStudio in the end.</p>
<p>We used the lunchbreak to pair people up using a direct videocall between
me and <a href="https://twitter.com/marcoemmrich">Marco</a>, but that is a cumbersome process and we'll try to
come up with a better one for next time (maybe use a Google spreadsheet
where each location can put down the interested parties' language, tooling
and communication preferences before?), but nonetheless all remote pairs 
reported having had fun!</p>
<p>Facilitating remote pairs is surprisingly easy, but only when the pairs use
the headphones which can be shared between two people - one bud in each person's
ear.</p>
<p>While it does require some prior coordination between the hosts (sync session 
start times, agree on the same constraint for the session, etc.), I do suggest
you try it out if you have the chance, especially if you haven't remote paired
before!</p>
          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2015/11/15/facilitating-the-global-day-of-coderetreat-zagreb-and-a-little-nuremberg-2015/">Facilitating the Global Day of Coderetreat Zagreb (and a little Nuremberg) 2015</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Day of Coderetreat 2012 - Nuremberg</title>
      <link>http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/12/global-day-of-coderetreat-2012-nuremberg.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2012 09:30:00 CET</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[code]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[code retreat]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[community]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[organizing]]></category>
      <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/12/global-day-of-coderetreat-2012-nuremberg.html</guid>
      <description>Global Day of Coderetreat 2012 - Nuremberg</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
          
<br/><br/><header> <div id="global-day-of-coderetreat-2012-nuremberg"></div></header><div class="post_prose"><blockquote>If you are not familiar with the concept of a  <a href="http://coderetreat.org/">code retreat</a>, listen to this  <a href="http://www.dotnetrocks.com/default.aspx?showNum=728">podcast</a> (or read the  <a href="http://s3.amazonaws.com/dnr/dotnetrocks_0728_corey_haines.pdf">transcript</a>).</blockquote>As you may remember, I've attended <a href="/2012/09/my-first-code-retreat-legacy-code.html">my first code retreat earlier this year in Frankfurt</a>. One of the reasons for attending was  that I had a nagging thought throughout organizing <a href="http://citconf.com/budapest2012/">CITCON Budapest</a> that I should do something locally too, and a coderetreat sounded just like the perfect thing. So I've came back with enough enthusiasm from Frankfurt to approach our CEO (Dirk) about <a href="http://www.paessler.com/">Paessler AG</a> helping me organize one in Nuremberg - and he offered the office to host it in and to pay for the lunch. Thus  the biggest obstacle was cleared.<br/><blockquote>The importance of this couldn't be emphasized. As I've seen on the <a href="http://globalday.coderetreat.org/">Global Day of Coderetreat</a> organizers' list, it has caused some headache and  worry for fellow hosts. And in addition to the fiscal support, my  colleagues went way beyond anything I expected - our sysadmins arranging the required technical &amp; security infrastructure, running <a href="http://www.paessler.com/blog/2012/11/21/other/paessler-is-one-of-the-hosts-of-the-global-day-of-coderetreat">the GDCR event on the  company blog</a>, and even non-programmer colleagues offering to  come by Saturday to help with anything if needed.  Thank you all, you made it really easy! (by the way, <a href="http://www.paessler.com/company/jobs">Paessler is hiring!</a>)</blockquote>Anyhow, this post will not be about the organization process, but about what I have learned on this day as a co-facilitator &amp; participant about code and people.<br/><blockquote>Another big thanks goes to <a href="http://twitter.com/marcoemrich">Marco Emrich</a>, a seasoned coderetreat facilitator, who helped getting the event off the ground and helped me getting  started facilitating (thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/NicoleRauch">Nicole</a> &amp; <a href="http://twitter.com/Ookami86">Johannes</a>  for introducing me to Marco!)</blockquote>The attendance was low (next time we'll schedule the start 30-60 minutes later), but I was surprised to learn how well the coderetreat functioned with so few participants. To ensure there is enough variety and that people have new pairs, we took turns with Marco coding (which we planned anyway in case of odd number of participants).<br/><h2 id="the-sessions">The Sessions</h2><ol><li>no constraints, getting familiar with the problem</li><li><a href="https://github.com/zsoldosp/zsoldosp-dotfiles/blob/master/bin/snippets/python/unitsofmeasure.py">no primitives</a> &amp; focus on the rules (fake out the world if needed at all)</li><li>Ping-Pong TDD &amp; naive implementation (with a switch at half time)</li><li>no conditional &amp; no mouse</li><li>baby steps</li><li>free to choose session</li></ol><h2 id="its-the-global-day-of-coderetreat">It's the <strong>Global</strong> Day of Coderetreat</h2>Even though we were only a few people here, it's been great to chat to the others elsewhere worldwide, saying hi to people doing exactly the same thing we do, just in various other  locations. While there were audio problems sometime, we didn't mind it. And next year we won't  bother with trying to schedule exact times for the calls, since we all will miss those times  anyway, but rather just rely on improvising video calls.<br/><h2 id="code-related-observations">Code Related Observations</h2><ul><li>It's really interesting to see other people programming. It is certainly not    something one gets to do during their day jobs (except maybe trainers, team leads, and mentors).   It is even more interesting to contrast the external observer's impressions/understanding   with the understanding of the people involved in the programming - the difference can be   huge. This might help understanding how many developers feel bosses/managers always misunderstand   their progress...</li><li>It's also interesting to track people across the different pairs and see whether    they bring their firm opinions (battle scars?) to each session or let go of them    to allow the opportunity to learn a different approach. This is not necessarily a bad    thing, but if you have plans to learn, beware of this and be explicit what you want to    learn - know whether you want to explore one idea and bounce it off/get it challenged by    many people or whether you want to simply see how others program and see if any of that    could be applicable to you. E.g.: it was pretty interesting to see how my F#/Scala inspired   ideas (case classes &amp; types) could be materialized in clojure. However, I have certainly   learned less about clojure than I would have had I let my partner do it as he would   in clojure natively (though the <em>no primitives</em> restriction was screaming   for types in my opinion).</li><li>We developers are really creative at finding (or at least looking for) loopholes in the   constraints. During the <em>no conditional</em> session one pair TDD'd a function returning a boolean   and claimed they had no conditionals in their code and were trying to convince us that   even the rest of the system wouldn't need conditionals to use this code... Or that returning   booleans is not an issue since they could refactor it into something that doesn't need to    return booleans once they get to the rest of the system... I'm certainly looking forward running    a <em>no return values allowed</em> session and see how people will circumvent that (and rationalize it   away)!</li><li>The longer you have worked with a tool/language, the more readily you accept and work around   its quirks. When we wanted to structure our tests the way we would describe <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway's_Game_of_Life">the four rules   of Conway's Game of Life</a> in writing (heading, then four subheadings, and then the concrete    examples under the subheadings) it didn't match RSpec's expectations at all. We agreed that both    structures (RSpec vs. the natural) make sense and we can understand how &amp; why RSpec evolved this way,   but we couldn't make it match the natural structure. This lead to a nice brief discussion about when    you want to deviate from standard tooling/processes and when one is better off following it.</li><li>Some people just can't put off the desire to finish the task. I will have to be conscious of this   in the future, and prod people more - e.g.: to ask whether this test &amp; app code meets their definition of   perfect.</li><li>Sometimes when things are hard, it is an indication that you are doing the wrong thing or solving the   wrong problem. E.g.: I wanted to write a test for our function to ensure that the function fails unless    it gets exactly 8 parameters (number of neighbors) but we were not supposed to use primitives. It felt   like enlightenment when my pair pointed out that there is nothing in the rules that mandate that requirement!</li><li><a href="http://www.infoq.com/presentations/TDD-as-if-You-Meant-It">TDD as if you meant it</a> is really hard unless both of you are good at the chosen   language. I assumed Ruby and Python are rather similar, but learned quickly it is not the    case. While we had great conversations during the session, and I've learned some interesting things about   Ruby, we have not made much progress with the actual constraint.</li><li>It seems most people work on their desktop machines/docking stations, and thus their laptop is   a secondary device, where they have not invested in their environments that much, and thus   the no mouse constraint is much harder (e.g.: having ReSharper installed at work, but not on   the personal laptop).</li></ul>... and I could go on much longer :) Certainly, the coderetreat format is great, and I enjoyed both programming and facilitating (though the fact my German is not strong enough makes it somewhat difficult),  and I'm sure we'll do more coderetreats in Nuremberg. So keep an eye out for it on the <a href="http://coderetreat.org/events/event/search?q=Nuremberg">coderetreat  site</a> or on the <a href="http://www.softwerkskammer.de/">Softwarekammer</a> events page.</div>

          <hr />
          The post <a hef="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu/2012/12/global-day-of-coderetreat-2012-nuremberg.html">Global Day of Coderetreat 2012 - Nuremberg</a> first appeared on <a href="http://blog.zsoldosp.eu">http://blog.zsoldosp.eu</a>.
        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
